<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Transl Med</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Translational Medicine</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1479-5876</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15283862</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC509287</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1479-5876-2-26</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1479-5876-2-26</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Commentary</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Cancer immunotherapy: avoiding the road to perdition</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chiriva-Internati</surname><given-names>Maurizio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>maurizio.chirivainternati@ttuhsc.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Grizzi</surname><given-names>Fabio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>fabio.grizzi@humanitas.it</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bright</surname><given-names>Robert K</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>Robert.Bright@ttmc.ttuhsc.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Martin Kast</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>mkast@usc.edu</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Microbiology &#x00026; Immunology and Southwest Cancer Treatment and Research Center, Texas Tech University Health Science Center, Lubbock, TX, 79430, USA</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Scientific Direction, Istituto Clinico Humanitas, Rozzano, 20089 Milan, Italy</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>"M. Rodriguez" Foundation &#x02013; Institute for Quantitative Methods in Medicine, 20100 Milan, Italy</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Norris Comprehensive Cancer Center, University of Southern California, Los Angeles, CA, 90089 USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>7</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.translational-medicine.com/content/2/1/26"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>6</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>7</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004 Chiriva-Internati et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Chiriva-Internati et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Chiriva-Internati
               Maurizio
               
               maurizio.chirivainternati@ttuhsc.edu
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Cancer immunotherapy: avoiding the road to perdition
         </dc:title><dc:date>2004</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Journal of Translational Medicine 2(1): 26-. (2004)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1479-5876(2004)2:1&#x0003c;26&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1479-5876</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><p>The hypothesis that human cancers express antigens that can be specifically targeted by cell mediated immunity has become a scientifically justifiable rationale for the design and clinical testing of novel tumor-associated antigens (TAA). Although a number of TAA have been recognized and it has been suggested that they could be useful in the immunological treatment of cancer, the complexity of human beings leads us to reflect on the need to establish new criteria for validating their real applicability. Herein, we show a system level-based approach that includes morphological and molecular techniques, which is specifically required to improve the capacity to produce desired results and to allow cancer immunotherapy to re-emerge from the mist in which it is currently shrouded.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Although considerable advances have been made in terms of our molecular and cellular knowledge, for most human disease states a fundamental understanding of causal disease onset, disease mechanism and progression, and optimal treatment is still significantly limited.</p><p>In part, this advancement has been hampered by our inability to fully and rapidly delineate complex cellular metabolic processes and molecular pathways.</p><p>Organisms are complex self-organizing entities made up of such parts: organs, tissues, cells, organelles and ultimately molecules and atoms. One question that arises, concerns the relationship between the whole and its component parts. The issue at stake is sometimes called "the question of reduction" or "the problem of reductionism" [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>].</p><p>The inefficacy of contemporary science to describe biological systems, consisting of non-identical parts that have different and non-local interactions has tended to limit progress in the human healthcare. Many biological systems remain incomprehensible because their multifarious nature has been combined with a reductionist approach based on the linear conception of <italic>cause </italic>and <italic>effect</italic>.</p><p>The use, however, of a more <italic>holistic </italic>multidimensional system level-based approach may provide new insights into the understanding of disease processes and mechanisms of action of therapeutical agents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p><p>Herein we aim to introduce a system level-based approach that includes morphological and molecular techniques for validating the appropriateness of using novel tumor-associated antigens (TAA) for clinical purposes. This approach might be easily implemented for identifying prognostic, diagnostic and alternative biomarkers.</p><p>Finally, this type of analysis of appropriately designed cohorts might also provide a key to understanding the differences in patients who do or do not respond to any particular therapy. This information may be helpful for a more effective (and therefore more <italic>cost-effective</italic>) design of clinical trials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Immunotherapy and the human complexity</title><p>The recognition and characterization of novel TAA is fundamental to the advance of cancer immunotherapy. The original hypothesis of Boon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] and Rosenberg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] that human cancers express antigens that can be specifically targeted by cell mediated immunity has become a scientifically justifiable rationale for the design and clinical testing of novel TAA based immunotherapies and therapeutic vaccines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>].</p><p>However, although a number of TAA have been discovered and it has been suggested that they could be useful in the immunological treatment of cancer, the <italic>complexity </italic>of human beings leads us to reflect on the need to establish compelling new criteria for validating their real applicability. <italic>Biological complexity </italic>can be intuitively appreciated &#x02013; at least in terms of morphological or behavioral complexity, or the variety of cell types in an organism &#x02013; but the term itself is notoriously difficult to define [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Human beings are <italic>complex hierarchical system</italic>s consisting of a number of <italic>levels of anatomical organization </italic>(genes, cells, tissues, organs, apparatuses, and organism) that interrelate differently with each other to form networks of growing complexity. The concept of anatomical entities as hierarchy of graduated forms, and the increasing number of known structural variables, have highlighted new properties of organized biological matter and raised a series of intriguing questions. In order to understand biology at the system <italic>level</italic>, we need to examine the structure and dynamics of the functions of organisms rather than the characteristics of their constitutive isolated parts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>].</p><p>The expression of TAA in biological materials has mainly been studied at the level of gene expression and gene level measurement by Reverse Transcriptase-Polymerase Chain Reaction (RT-PCR) analysis and the Quantitative real-time PCR (qrt-PCR) technology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. However, the <italic>information </italic>provided by these approaches is limited by the fact that the phenomena observed at each level of anatomical organization have properties that do not exist at a lower or higher level: RT-PCR and qrt-PCR may offer a satisfactory <italic>qualitative/quantitative </italic>description of <italic>small-scale structures</italic>, but this is likely to be irrelevant when it comes to <italic>large-scale features</italic>. The above considerations, in conjunction with the <italic>complexity of tumor-host interactions </italic>within the tumor microenvironment caused by temporal changes in tumor phenotypes and an array of immune mediators expressed in the tumor microenvironment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] might clarify the limited reliability and applicability of current immunotherapeutic approaches.</p><p>Here, we suggest a <italic>system level-based </italic>approach (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>) for validating the appropriateness of using TAA for clinical purposes, which includes the following never defined before key points:</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>System level-based approach for validating candidate TAA for clinical application. Aside from the well defined experimental procedure, the method presented here is based on the <italic>complex hierarchical nature </italic>of the human beings. The analysis begins at level of gene expression and then continues to higher levels of anatomical organization, (cell, tissue, organ, apparatuses and organism). This approach includes both morphological and molecular techniques. It also introduces the concept of dynamics of TAA expression at the level of the <italic>cell cycle</italic>, the <italic>physiological status of the organism </italic>and the <italic>process of aging</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1479-5876-2-26-1"/></fig><p>&#x02022; <italic>Discriminating </italic>the <italic>cell types </italic>expressing the candidate antigen on the basis of the morphological visualization of all of the parts making up the <italic>organ </italic>under investigation.</p><p>&#x02022; <italic>Discriminating </italic>the candidate antigen's sub-cellular localization (at the level of cell <italic>nucleus</italic>, <italic>cytoplasm </italic>and/or <italic>plasma membrane</italic>) by ultra-structural morphological visualizations.</p><p>&#x02022; <italic>Mapping </italic>candidate antigen expression in all of the <italic>organs </italic>making up the <italic>apparatuses</italic>.</p><p>&#x02022; <italic>Mapping </italic>candidate antigen expression in all of the <italic>apparatuses </italic>making up the living <italic>organism</italic>.</p><p>&#x02022; <italic>Estimating </italic>the percentage of normal cells and their neoplastic counterparts expressing the candidate antigen.</p><p>&#x02022; <italic>Evaluating </italic>the <italic>dynamics </italic>of candidate antigen expression at the level of the <italic>cell cycle</italic>, the <italic>physiological status of the organism </italic>(<italic>i.e. </italic>the woman's menstrual cycle) and the <italic>process of aging</italic>.</p><p>In order to advance our knowledge in a currently widely debated field of investigation, a clearer distinction must be made between <italic>in vitro </italic>laboratory results (the discovery and validation of target antigens) and their <italic>in vivo </italic>application (<italic>in vivo </italic>validation), and it is necessary to adopt a more complete experimental approach that forcefully includes both morphological and molecular techniques [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Translational science which is aimed to test, in humans, novel therapeutic strategies developed through experimentation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>] should begin to consider the role of <italic>emergence </italic>in other words the appearance of <italic>unexpected structures </italic>and/or the occurrence of <italic>surprising behaviors </italic>in large systems composed from microscopic parts, whether physical or biological. By unexpected and surprising we mean structures and behaviors which are not <italic>intuitive </italic>and are not simply <italic>predictable</italic>.</p><p>Since our understanding of complex human disease such as cancer, is still limited and pre-clinical models have shown a discouraging propensity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] to fail when applied to humans, a new way of thinking is strongly needed that unites physicians, biologists, mathematicians and epidemiologists, in order to develop a better theoretical framework of tumor development, progression and tumor-host interactions.</p><p>Although the model presented here is based on a multidisciplinary system-level approach probably within the reach of only very large and multi-talented laboratories, it is aimed to introduce a different way of investigating <italic>human cancer, </italic>which takes into account the complexity of the human being as a system.</p><p>The use of a holistic approach, which enables a more accurate selection of immunotherapeutic target antigens in the first phase of the experimental research, will reduce the notable fragmentation of the biological information in the post-genomic era, and will facilitate a more accurate transfer of the acquired knowledge to the bedside.</p><p>Further, this new multidisciplinary approach is specifically required to improve the capacity to produce desired results with a minimum expenditure of <italic>energy</italic>, <italic>time</italic>, or <italic>resources </italic>for immunotherapeutic treatments and to allow cancer immunotherapy to re-emerge from the mist in which it is currently shrouded.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ayala</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Yates FE</surname></name></person-group><source>In Self-Organizing Systems-The Emergence of Order</source><year>1987</year><publisher-name>New York and London: Plenum Press</publisher-name><fpage>315</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morel</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Greef</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Marple</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Clish</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Loscalzo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Naylor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primer on medical genomics. Part XIV: Introduction to systems biology &#x02013; a new approach to understanding disease and treatment</article-title><source>Mayo Clin Proc</source><year>2004</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>651</fpage><lpage>658</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15132407</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van der Bruggen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Traversari</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chomez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lurquin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>De Plaen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Van den Eynde</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Knuth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Boon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A gene encoding an antigen recognized by cytolytic T lymphocytes on a human melanoma</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1991</year><volume>254</volume><fpage>1643</fpage><lpage>1647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1840703</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawakami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Eliyahu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivoltini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Topalian</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Miki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cloning of the gene coding for a shared human melanoma antigen recognized by autologous T cells infiltrating into tumor</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1994</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>3515</fpage><lpage>3519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8170938</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer vaccines: finding the best way to train the immune system</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>2002</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>1523</fpage><lpage>1526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12381703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jnci/94.20.1523</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Reilly</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bright</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tumor-associated antigens: from discovery to immunity</article-title><source>Int Rev Immunol</source><year>2003</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12962271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08830180305221</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gilboa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The promise of cancer vaccines</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><year>2004</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>401</fpage><lpage>411</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15122211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrc1359</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szathmary</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular biology and evolution. Can genes explain biological complexity?</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2001</year><volume>292</volume><fpage>1315</fpage><lpage>1316</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11360989</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1060852</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling the heart&#x02013;from genes to cells to the whole organ</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2002</year><volume>295</volume><fpage>1678</fpage><lpage>1682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11872832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1069881</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nurse</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reductionism. The ends of understanding</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1997</year><volume>387</volume><fpage>657</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9192884</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/42600</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bock G, Goode JA</surname></name></person-group><article-title>The limits of Reductionism in Biology</article-title><source>Novartis Found Symp</source><year>1998</year><volume>213</volume><publisher-name>John Wiley, London</publisher-name><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9653718</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computational systems biology</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2002</year><volume>295</volume><fpage>1662</fpage><lpage>1664</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11872829</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1069492</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldenfeld</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadanoff</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simple lessons from complexity</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1999</year><volume>284</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10102823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.284.5411.87</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Juretic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Spagnoli</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultz-Thater</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarcevic</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer/testis tumour-associated antigens: immunohistochemical detection with monoclonal antibodies</article-title><source>Lancet Oncol</source><year>2003</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12573352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(03)00982-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Periman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Klug</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Weidanz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitton</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiriva-Internati</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Defining tumor antigens: mRNA, protein or cytotoxicity?</article-title><source>Trends Immunol</source><year>2002</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>236</fpage><lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12102740</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1471-4906(02)02196-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schultze</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Vonderheide</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From cancer genomics to cancer immunotherapy: toward second-generation tumor antigens</article-title><source>Trends Immunol</source><year>2001</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>516</fpage><lpage>523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11525943</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1471-4906(01)02015-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mocellin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilati</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nitti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Marincola</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular oncology in the post-genomic era: the challenge of proteomics</article-title><source>Trends Mol Med</source><year>2003</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12763523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1471-4914(03)00047-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marincola</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Herlyn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Seliger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrone</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tumors as elusive targets of T-cell-based active immunotherapy</article-title><source>Trends Immunol</source><year>2003</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12810110</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiriva-Internati</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grizzi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Franceschini</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kast</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is sperm protein 17 a useful target for tumor immunotherapy?</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2003</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>2308</fpage><lpage>2309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12959941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2003-05-1747</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marincola</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Translational Medicine: A two-way road</article-title><source>J Transl Med</source><year>2003</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14527344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1479-5876-1-1</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



