<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Carcinog</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Carcinogenesis</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1477-3163</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15707498</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC549518</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1477-3163-4-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1477-3163-4-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Colonic Paneth cell metaplasia is pre-neoplastic condition of colonic cancer or not?</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>Ryo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>ryo5573@q01.itscom.net</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>Toshikazu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>ryo5573@q01.itscom.net</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tadokoro</surname><given-names>Kenichi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>ryo5573@q01.itscom.net</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>The Department of Pathology, Juntendo Izunagaoka Hospital of Juntendo University School of Medicine, Shizuoka, Japan</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>The Department of Pathology(I), Juntendo University School of Medicine, Tokyo, Japan</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>R &#x00026; D Center, Biomedical Laboratories, Inc, Kawagoe, Japan</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>2</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.carcinogenesis.com/content/4/1/5"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>10</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>2</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Wada et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Wada et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Wada
               Ryo
               
               
               ryo5573@q01.itscom.net
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Colonic Paneth cell metaplasia is pre-neoplastic condition of colonic cancer or not?
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Journal of Carcinogenesis 4(1): 5-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1477-3163(2005)4:1&#x0003c;5&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1477-3163</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The carcinogenesis of colorectal cancer has been accepted by a model for a cascade of genetic alterations, named the adenoma-carcinoma sequence. In order to elucidate the carcinogenesis of the colorectal cancer more clearly, the genetic abnormalies of the non-neoplastic mucosal epithelium of the colon and rectum should be investigated. It has been speculated that colonic Paneth cell metaplasia (PaM) is one of the pre-neoplastic mucosa of colonic cancer. Therefore, we studied the propria mucosa of the right colon with PaM from the standpoints of the frequency of the K-ras codon 12 mutations (K-ras), which is initial genetic abnormality in colorectal cancer, and the loss of heterozygosity of microsatellite markers (LOH-MS), which has a relationship to development of colorectal cancer.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>Fifty-two regions with PaM histopathologically from 12 surgically resected right colon specimens were studied. DNA extraction of the colonic mucosa with PaM was obtained using a microdissection method, and the frequency of the K-ras of PaM was investigated by enriched polymerase chain reaction-enzyme linked mini-sequence assay, and the frequency of the LOH-MS (D2S123, D17S250 and D5S346) of PaM was examined by high resolution fluorescenced labeled PCR primers.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>K-ras mutation was detected in fifteen regions among 52 PaM (28.9%). All mutations were a single mutation and GGT changed to AGT in eleven and GAT in four. LOH-MS were detected in twenty-one regions among 52 PaM (40.4%) (D2S123: 35.4%, 17/48 regions, D17S250: 13.7%, 7/51 regions, and D5S346: 0%, 0/52 regions). No K-ras mutations and LOH-MS were detected in the controls (Colorectal mucosa with no PaM).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Colonic mucosa with Paneth cell metaplasia may be one of the pre-neoplastic mucosa in the development of the colonic epithelial neoplasia.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Paneth cell metaplasia</kwd><kwd>K-ras mutation</kwd><kwd>loss of heterozygosity of microsatellite marker</kwd><kwd>colorectal cancer</kwd><kwd>microdissection</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Vogelstein et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>] have reported the involvement of multistage genetic abnormalities in the development of colorectal cancers, and pointed out that K-ras mutation is the initial genetic abnormality in the adenoma-carcinoma sequence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>] of the development of the colorectal cancer. Recently, some reports have pointed out that the replication errors and loss of heterozygosity of the microsatellite markers have the development of the colorectal cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>].</p><p>However, the genetic abnormalities of the non-neoplastic mucosal epithelium of the colon and rectum has not been investigated, except the aberrant crypt foci [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] and hyperplastic polyp [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>], although the colorectal epithelial neoplasia is derived from the colorectal mucosal epithelium. For the preventive medicine, the genetic abnormalities of the pre-neoplastic mucosa of the colorectal cancer should be known.</p><p>We have speculated previously that the colorectal Paneth cell metaplasia (PaM) is one of pre-neoplastic mucosa on the development of the colorectal epithelial neoplasias [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>], because PaM were seen very frequently in the adjacent mucosa to the minute-sized colorectal epithelial neoplasias as well as within these neoplasias.</p><p>The main purpose of the present study was to investigate the frequencies of the K-ras codon 12 mutations (K-ras) and the loss of heterozygosity of dinucleotide microsatellite markers (LOH-MS) in the propria mucosa with PaM of the right colon.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>The materials were 12 surgically resected specimens of right colon, which had the colonic carcinomas were present, and histological diagnosis was assessed at the Department of Pathology, Juntendo Izunagaoka Hospital. Although we have intended to investigate the PaM in the normal colon of the individuals without cancer, using the biopsies specimens, it was difficult to detect the PaM in these specimens. No inflammatory bowel diseases were included in the materials. Informed consent was obtained from all the patients to investigate the genetic alterations in the current study.</p><p>The specimens were fixed in 10 % buffered formalin solution and prepared by cutting the non-neoplasitic area into 3 &#x02013; 5 mm sections. Each section was embedded in paraffin and stained with hematoxylin and eosin (HE), followed by immunohistochemical staining for anti-lysozyme (DAKO, Japan). Immunohistochemical stainings were performed by the avidin-biotin-peroxidase-complex method, at dilution of 1 : 100.</p><p>Fifty-two colonic mucosal regions with PaM, distant from neoplastic lesion, aberrant crypt foci and hyperplastic polyp, were detected by HE staining and anti-lysozyme antibody staining, and these mucosa were used as the target regions in the current study.</p><p>All paraffin blocks of the target regions and 12 paraffin blocks with no PaM as controls of each materials were used for the DNA extraction.</p><sec><title>DNA extraction</title><p>Paraffin blocks with the target foci mentioned above were prepared for DNA extraction. The target foci were microdissected using a 20-gauge needle, comparing the slide with HE staining in the same position. The extracted DNA was diluted with 5 ml of TaKaRa DEXPAT (for DNA Extraction from Paraffin-embedded Tissue, TaKaRa Biomedical Inc.).</p></sec><sec><title>Analysis of the K-ras</title><p>Mutation of K-ras was analyzed and compared by enriched polymerase chain reaction-enzyme linked mini-sequence assay (PCR-ELMA). In PCR-ELMA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>], upstream primer for the first and second PCR was 5'-TAAACTTGTGGTAGTTGG-AACT-3', downstream primer for the first PCR was 5'-GTTGGATCA-TATTCGTC-CAC-3', and downstream for primer the second PCR was 5'-CAAATGAT-CTGA-ATTAGCTG-3'. The first PCR reaction was performed containing 1 &#x003bc;L of DNA lysate, 100 &#x003bc;M dNTP, 1.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 &#x003bc;M each primer, 0.625 U Taq DNA polymerase and 1 &#x000d7; PCR buffer [containing 10 mM Tris-HCl(pH 8.3 at 25 degrees of temperature), 50 mM KCl and 0.001%(w/v) gelatin] in a thermal cycler. Then, 10 &#x003bc;L of the denatured second PCR product was hybridized with probes to detect the K-ras codon 12 wild-type (GGT) and six mutant (GAT, GCT, GTT, AGT, CGT and TGT) DNAs were immobilized, at 55 degrees of temperature for 30 minutes, and 100 &#x003bc;L of biotinylated A and 0.01 U of TdqDNA polypmerase were added and incubation was continued at 55 degrees of temperature for 30 minutes.</p><p>For development, 100 &#x003bc;L of avidin-horseradish peroxidase conjugate was added and the reaction was performed at room temperature for 30 minutes. Then, 100 &#x003bc;L of tetramethyl-benzidine (TMB) substrate was added and the plates were left to develop in the dark at room temperature for 20 minutes. Finally, 100 &#x003bc;L of stop solution was contained and the light absorbance of each sample was measured by spectrophotometry (Multiskan Multisoft, Labsystems, Tokyo) with a 450 nm filter wavelength (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Enriched polymerase chain reaction-enzyme linked mini-sequence assay (PCR-ELMA), showing K-ras codon 12 mutation in the colonic Paneth cell metaplasia. AGT-type mutation was seen in line 3.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1477-3163-4-5-1"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Analysis of the LOH-MS</title><p>Although we have intended to investigate the frequency of microsatellite instabilities using five microsatellite markers, which has been recommended by National Cancer Institute[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>], the replication error or microsatellite instabilities could not be detected. Although the true reasons for these failures was not know, we may think that the target foci were too small and post-formalin solution condition with long time.</p><p>Therefore, only LOH was investigated described below. Three dinucleotide microsatellite markers (D2S123, D17S250 and D5S346) were selected for LOH among the microsatellite markers, recommended by National Cancer Institute, because commonly it has been thought to be difficult to study the LOH using mononucleotide microsatellite markers.</p><p>These LOH-MS were investigated using high resolution fluorescenced labeled PCR primers in proportion to the method of Tsuchida et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. The outline of it : 1. PCR was performed containing 1 &#x003bc;L of DNA lysate, 100 &#x003bc;M dNTP, 1.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 &#x003bc;M each primer marked with fluorescent dye of three colors as blue, green and yellow, 0.625 U Taq DNA polymerase and 1 &#x000d7; PCR buffer [containing 10 mM Tris-HCl(pH 8.3 at 25&#x000b0;C), 50 mM KCl and 0.001%(w/v) gelatin] in a thermal cycler. 2. The electrophoresis was conducted 2 hours by means of an ABI-377 DNA auto-sequencer (PE Biosystems, Inc., Foster City, CA, USA). 3. A comparison was made of peaks of same marker arising from normal tissue and the propria mucosa with PaM, using the Gene Scan TM waveform analyzed softwave, and LOH were assessed. That is to say, LOH (+) was assessed when the ratio of the peak area of (the propria mucosa with PaM/normal tissue) was less than 70 % or was more than 143 %.</p><p>The data were analyzed statistically with Student's t-test (t-test) and chi-square test ; a p-value of less than 0.05 was considered to be significant.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>)</title><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>K-ras mutation and the loss of heterozygosity of microsatellitemarkers of colonic Paneth cell metaplasia</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="center">K-ras*</td><td align="center">D2S123</td><td align="center">D17S250</td><td align="center">D5S346</td><td align="center">Total LOH*</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">PaM</td><td align="center">28.9%</td><td align="center">35.4%</td><td align="center">13.7%</td><td align="center">0%</td><td align="center">40.4%</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">(15/52)</td><td align="center">(17/48)</td><td align="center">(7/51)</td><td align="center">(0/52)</td><td align="center">(21/52)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Normal</td><td align="center">0%</td><td align="center">0%</td><td align="center">0%</td><td align="center">0%</td><td align="center">0%</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">(0/8)</td><td align="center">(0/8)</td><td align="center">(0/8)</td><td align="center">(0/8)</td><td align="center">(0/8)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>PaM : Colonic Paneth cell metaplasia,</p><p>Normal : Normal colonic mucosa, K-ras : K-ras codon 12 mutation,</p><p>* : between PaM and Normal, p &#x0003c; 0.01, chi-square test</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>K-ras mutation was detected in fifteen regions among 52 PaM (28.9 %). All mutations were a single mutation. For K-ras mutation patterns, 11 showed GGT to AGT, and four showed to GAT.</p><p>LOH-MS was detected in twenty-one regions among 52 PaM (40.4 %) (D2S123: 35.4 %, 17/48 regions, D17S250: 13.7 %, 7/51 regions, and D5S346: 0 %, 0/52 regions). No K-ras mutations and LOH-MS were detected in the controls (Colorectal mucosa with no PaM, no neoplastic lesion, no aberrant crypt foci and no hyperplastic polyp).</p><p>Thus, the frequency of both K-ras mutation and LOH-MS in the colonic mucosa with PaM were significantly higher than those of the controls (p &#x0003c; 0.01, chi-square test).</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>K-ras mutations have been detected in several human neoplasias [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>], and it has been pointed out that K-ras mutation is the initial genetic abnormality in the development of the colorectal cancers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Recently, the replication errors of the gene is thought to be important in the development of the colorectal cancer. And the loss of heterozygosity of the microsatellite markers, which are often used as the targets in the investigation for the replication errors of the gene, is also considered to be important in the development of the colorectal cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Namely, the carcinogenesis of colorectal cancer is almost clarified.</p><p>In order to conclude the carcinogenesis of the colorectal cancer more clearly, the genetic abnormality of the non-neoplastic mucosal epithelium of the colon and rectum should be investigated, however, because the colorectal cancers are derived from the colorectal mucosa. It is also important for the preventive medicine of the colorectal cancer to know the carcinogenesis of it.</p><p>However, until now, the genetic abnormalities of the colorectal non-neoplastic mucosa is unclear, except the aberrant crypt foci [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] and hyperplastic polyp [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>].</p><p>We have already reported that the colorectal Paneth cell metaplasia (PaM) is one of pre-neoplastic mucosa on the development of the colorectal epithelial neoplasias [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>], because PaM were seen very frequently in the adjacent mucosa to the minute-sized colorectal epithelial neoplasias and within these neoplasias.</p><p>Therefore, K-ras mutation and the loss of heterozygosity of microsatellite markers of PaM were investigated in this study, and the current study is thought to be the first report focusing on this.</p><p>Our results showed that K-ras mutation was detected in fifteen regions among 52 PaM (28.9%), and LOH-MS was detected in twenty-one regions among 52 PaM (40.4%).</p><p>Namely, K-ras mutation and LOH-MS of PaM were not rare and the frequency of those of PaM were higher than those of the normal colonic mucosa, and it came to light that some PaM had the genetic abnormalities which had a relationship to the development of colorectal cancer.</p><p>Paneth cells, which are usually situated at the base of the glands of the small intestine, were first identified by Scwalbe [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] in 1872, were studied in detail morphologically by Paneth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>] in 1888.</p><p>Now, these cells have been one of the most famous cells in the gastro-intestinal tract, however, the detail function of these is not clear. Paneth cells are sometimes seen in the colorectal tubules, for example in the proximal colonic mucosa of elderly subjects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>], in patients with ulcerative colitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] and colonic epithelial neoplasia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>], although the reasons why Paneth cells appear in the large bowel is still unknown.</p><p>Described above, many riddles about Paneth cell are still remained. And the gene abnormalities of colonic mucosa with PaM in the current study may be not equal to those of single Paneth cell in the colonic mucosa, because it is difficult to obtain only single Paneth cell in the colonic mucosa, even if microdissection method is used.</p><p>However, we have been able to investigate the colonic mucosa with PaM, and we think it very interesting that some PaM have K-ras mutation and the loss of heterozygosity of microsatellite markers, and these PaM may be thought to be the pre-neoplastic mucosa in development of the colonic epithelial neoplasia. Further molecular studies concerning Paneth cell metaplasia in the large bowel should be warranted.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Colonic mucosa with Paneth cell metaplasia may be one of the pre-neoplastic mucosa in the development of the colonic epithelial neoplasia.</p></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>PaM, colonic Paneth cell metaplasia; K-ras, K-ras codon 12 mutations; LOH-MS, loss of heterozygosity of microsatellite markers; HE, hematoxylin and eosin; PCR, polymerase chain reaction; ELMA, enzyme linked mini-sequence assay</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors thank Mr D Mrozek for assistance with the manuscript.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vogelstein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fearon</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Genetic alterations during colorectal tumour development</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1988</year><volume>319</volume><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>532</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2841597</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morson</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The polyp-cancer sequence in the large bowel</article-title><source>Proc Soc Med</source><year>1974</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>457</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thibodeau</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bren</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaid</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microsatellite instability in cancer of the proximal colon</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1993</year><volume>260</volume><fpage>816</fpage><lpage>819</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8484122</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Senba</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Konishi Okamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Clinicopathologic and genetic features of nonfamilial colorectal carcinomas with DNA replication errors</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>1998</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9445183</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Penner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Somatic APC and K-ras codon 12 mutations in aberrant crypt foci from human colons</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>1994</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>5527</fpage><lpage>5530</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7923190</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Otori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Oda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>High frequency of K-ras mutations in human colorectal hyperplastic polyps</article-title><source>Gut</source><year>1997</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>660</fpage><lpage>663</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9203947</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Miwa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Incidence of Paneth cells in minute tubular adenomas and adenocarcinomas of the large bowel</article-title><source>Acta Pathol Jpn</source><year>1992</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>579</fpage><lpage>584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1449053</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsubayashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Difference in mucus and K-ras mutation in relation to phenotypes of tumors of the papilla of Vater</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>1999</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>596</fpage><lpage>607</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10440687</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>K-ras codon 12 mutations of the super-minute dysplasia in the Barrett's esophagus by DNA extraction using a microdissection method</article-title><source>Dis Esophagus</source><year>2003</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>214</fpage><lpage>217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14641312</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1442-2050.2003.00331.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Thibodeau</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamiloton</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>A National Cancer Institute Workshop on microsatellite instability for cancer detection and familial predisposition : Development of international criteria for the determination of microsatellite instability in colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>1998</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>5248</fpage><lpage>5257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9823339</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsuchida</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasuya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Micro-satellite instability in multiple and single gastric cancers using fluorescent and auto-sequencer</article-title><source>Ann Cancer Res Ther</source><year>2000</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>112</fpage><lpage>124</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lord</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Grady</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheehan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>K-ras codon 12 mutations in Barrett's oesophagus and adenocarcinomas of the oesophagus and oesophagastric junction</article-title><source>J Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><year>2000</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>730</fpage><lpage>736</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10937677</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1440-1746.2000.02163.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Okabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Anraku</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Activation of the c-K-ras oncogene in a human pancreas carcinoma</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>1985</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>168</fpage><lpage>174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3855240</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin-Zanca</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Malignant activation of a K-ras oncogene in lung carcinoma but not in normal tissue of the same patient</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1984</year><volume>223</volume><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>664</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6695174</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scwalbe</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Beitrage zur Kenntniss der Drusen in den Darmwandungen in's Besondere Brunnerschen Drusen</article-title><source>Arch Mikroskop Anat</source><year>1872</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>140</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paneth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Uber die secrerineierenden Zellen des Dunndarm-Epithels</article-title><source>Arch Mikroskop Anat</source><year>1888</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>191</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Antonioli</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mucosal biopsy of the rectum, colon and distal ileum</article-title><source>Hum Pathol</source><year>1982</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>981</fpage><lpage>1012</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6759364</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Paneth cell metaplasia in ulcerative colitis</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><year>1961</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13733293</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neoplastic Paneth cells ; their occurence in 2 adenomas and one carcinoma of the colon</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>1965</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1416</fpage><lpage>1422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5844158</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incidence and significance of argentaffin and Paneth cells in some tumours of the large intestine</article-title><source>J Clin Path</source><year>1967</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>826</fpage><lpage>831</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5614067</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



