<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Cell Biology</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2121</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15760480</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC555532</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2121-6-13</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2121-6-13</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Ca<sup>2+ </sup>regulation in the absence of the <italic>iplA </italic>gene product in <italic>Dictyostelium discoideum</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schaloske</surname><given-names>Ralph H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>rschalos@chem.ucsd.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lusche</surname><given-names>Daniel F</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>Daniel.Lusche@web.de</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bezares-Roder</surname><given-names>Karen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>KBezares@web.de</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Happle</surname><given-names>Kathrin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>Kathrin.Happle@dr-mayr.de</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Malchow</surname><given-names>Dieter</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>Renate.Gimmi@uni-konstanz.de</email></contrib><contrib id="A6" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schlatterer</surname><given-names>Christina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>Christina.Schlatterer@uni-konstanz.de</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry, University of California at San Diego, 9500 Gilman Drive, La Jolla, CA 92093-0601, USA</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Faculty for Biology, University of Konstanz, 78457 Konstanz, Germany</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>3</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2121/6/13"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>11</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>3</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Schaloske et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Schaloske et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Schaloske
               H
               Ralph
               
               rschalos@chem.ucsd.edu
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Ca2+ regulation in the absence of the iplA gene product in Dictyostelium discoideum
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Cell Biology 6(1): 13-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1471-2121(2005)6:1&#x0003c;13&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1471-2121</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Stimulation of <italic>Dictyostelium discoideum </italic>with cAMP evokes an elevation of the cytosolic free Ca<sup>2+ </sup>concentration ([Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>). The [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-change is composed of liberation of stored Ca<sup>2+ </sup>and extracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup>-entry. The significance of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-transient for chemotaxis is under debate. Abolition of chemotactic orientation and migration by Ca<sup>2+</sup>-buffers in the cytosol indicates that a [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-increase is required for chemotaxis. Yet, the <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>mutant disrupted in a gene bearing similarity to IP<sub>3</sub>-receptors of higher eukaryotes aggregates despite the absence of a cAMP-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-transient which favours the view that [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-changes are insignificant for chemotaxis.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We investigated Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes and the effect of their disturbance on chemotaxis and development of <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells. Differentiation was altered as compared to wild type amoebae and sensitive towards manipulation of the level of stored Ca<sup>2+</sup>. Chemotaxis was impaired when [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-transients were suppressed by the presence of a Ca<sup>2+</sup>-chelator in the cytosol of the cells. Analysis of ion fluxes revealed that capacitative Ca<sup>2+</sup>-entry was fully operative in the mutant. In suspensions of intact and permeabilized cells cAMP elicited extracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup>-influx and liberation of stored Ca<sup>2+</sup>, respectively, yet to a lesser extent than in wild type. In suspensions of partially purified storage vesicles ATP-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup>-uptake and Ca<sup>2+</sup>-release activated by fatty acids or Ca<sup>2+</sup>-ATPase inhibitors were similar to wild type. Mn<sup>2+</sup>-quenching of fura2 fluorescence allows to study Ca<sup>2+</sup>-influx indirectly and revealed that the responsiveness of mutant cells was shifted to higher concentrations: roughly 100 times more Mn<sup>2+ </sup>was necessary to observe agonist-induced Mn<sup>2+</sup>-influx. cAMP evoked a [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-elevation when stores were strongly loaded with Ca<sup>2+</sup>, again with a similar shift in sensitivity in the mutant. In addition, basal [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i </sub>was significantly lower in <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>than in wild type amoebae.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>These results support the view that [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-transients are essential for chemotaxis and differentiation. Moreover, capacitative and agonist-activated ion fluxes are regulated by separate pathways that are mediated either by two types of channels in the plasma membrane or by distinct mechanisms coupling Ca<sup>2+</sup>-release from stores to Ca<sup>2+</sup>-entry in <italic>Dictyostelium</italic>. The <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>strain retains the capacitative Ca<sup>2+</sup>-entry pathway and an impaired agonist-activated pathway that operates with reduced efficiency or at higher ionic pressure.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Aggregation of <italic>Dictyostelium discoideum </italic>proceeds by an oriented migration of the amoebae towards a source of the attractant cAMP which is synthesized and released periodically by cells in the center of the aggregate. Stimulation with cAMP activates liberation of stored Ca<sup>2+ </sup>and extracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup>-entry [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>] leading to a [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-transient [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Chemotaxis proceeds in the presence of extracellular EGTA but not in the presence of intracellular Ca<sup>2+ </sup>buffers, so a [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-elevation is necessary and release of stored Ca<sup>2+ </sup>is sufficient for oriented migration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. On the other hand, the view that a [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-increase is essential for chemotaxis was called into question by analysis of a cell line where the <italic>iplA </italic>gene was disrupted by homologous recombination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. The <italic>iplA </italic>gene is the only gene known in the <italic>Dicyostelium </italic>genome so far that shares homology with IP<sub>3</sub>-receptors of higher eukaryotes. However, whether its protein product indeed constitutes a functional IP<sub>3</sub>-receptor and its cellular localization are not known. The <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>mutant was found to aggregate and to form fruiting bodies although neither cAMP-activated <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup>-entry nor a [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-elevation were detected [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. From these results the authors concluded that the <italic>iplA </italic>gene product is central to the regulation of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i </sub>and that its presence and thus the presence of an agonist-activated [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-increase is not necessary for proper chemotaxis and development. However, agents that interfere with IP<sub>3</sub>-receptor mediated signaling such as XestosponginC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>] were found to influence not only cAMP-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes but also the chemotactic response and aggregation of <italic>Dictyostelium </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. In this study we aimed to clarify these conflicting findings and analyzed both, capacitative and chemoattractant-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes and the effect of their disturbance on chemotaxis and differentiation of the <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>mutant. Mn<sup>2+</sup>-influx was used to determine the rates of ion fluxes into cells with filled and emptied stores and related to Ca<sup>2+</sup>-electrode recordings in cell suspensions. We found that ion fluxes, chemotaxis and differentiation were sensitive towards alteration of the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-homeostasis. Capacitative Ca<sup>2+</sup>-entry was normal in the mutant and upon stimulation with agonist Ca<sup>2+</sup>- and Mn<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes occurred, yet to a considerably reduced extent. Spontaneous motility and chemotactic performance of mutant amoebae was strongly impaired by the intracellular presence of a Ca<sup>2+</sup>-chelator.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Extracellular [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] affects development and chemotaxis of wild type and <italic>iplA</italic><sup>-</sup></title><p>As <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells formed fruiting bodies, albeit somewhat smaller in size, it was concluded that chemotactic aggregation and differentiation was normal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. We analyzed development of the mutant in parallel with wild type at various conditions. When cells differentiated on H5-agar plates (control situation) we consistently found a delay in the onset of aggregation by 1&#x02013;2 h in the mutant; the smaller size of fruiting bodies was due to breaking of aggregation strands yielding smaller mounds (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Next we asked whether the absence or presence of Ca<sup>2+ </sup>affects development. Differentiation on EGTA-containing agar plates and thus the steady reduction of internal Ca<sup>2+</sup>-levels dose dependently resulted in a delay of aggregation and a decrease in the size of aggregates and fruiting bodies in both strains. Doses of 5&#x02013;10 mM EGTA in the agar did not significantly alter the time point of aggregation which is in accordance with previous data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] showing requirement of additional multiple washing of amoebae with EGTA in order to affect aggregation. At concentrations of 15&#x02013;20 mM EGTA however, aggregation occurred at later time points (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>), on average at 13 &#x000b1; 3 h in wild type and at 19 &#x000b1; 2 h in <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells (mean &#x000b1; s.e.m. from 5 experiments); despite the daily variations in aggregation timing the mutant strain was delayed as compared to the wild type in each of the experiments performed. On the other hand, the presence of Ca<sup>2+ </sup>in the agar and therefore the continuous loading of cells with Ca<sup>2+ </sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>] resulted in stronger impairment of aggregation in the wild type. The delayed aggregation of wild type cells in the presence of Ca<sup>2+ </sup>was not due to inhibition of chemotaxis (see below). Now the formation of aggregates was observed consistently at earlier time points in the <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>strain than in wild type (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>; on average 7 &#x000b1; 0.5 h vs. 15 &#x000b1; 5 h until aggregate formation in <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>and wild type amoebae, respectively, at 20 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>in 6 independent experiments); indeed, under this condition differentiation of <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells resembled that of wild type observed in the control situation.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells have an altered pattern of development. Differentiation of the mutant and the wild type strain was assayed in parallel on agar plates. Cells at different time points of development on H5-agar are shown. Wild type amoebae aggregated at t<sub>7</sub>, whereas aggregation of the mutant strain was delayed and aggregation strands broke (t<sub>10</sub>); therefore, smaller fruiting bodies were formed as compared to the wild type. The full width of the image corresponds to 12.5 mm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-6-13-1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Development of <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells is impaired by depletion of internal Ca<sup>2+</sup>-stores due to EGTA-treatment. Differentiation of the wild type and the mutant on plates containing 20 mM EGTA is shown. Aggregation was delayed in both strains till t<sub>15 </sub>and t<sub>18 </sub>in wild type and <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells, respectively. The size of the aggregates and the fruiting bodies were much smaller than under control conditions. The full width of the image corresponds to 12.5 mm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-6-13-2"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>In the presence of external Ca<sup>2 </sup>aggregation is accelerated in <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells. Differentiation of the mutant and the wild type strain was assayed in parallel on agar plates supplemented with 20 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>. Aggregate formation occurred earlier in <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells (at t<sub>7</sub>) than in wild type (starting at t<sub>19</sub>) in the presence of Ca<sup>2+</sup>. The full width of the image corresponds to 12.5 mm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-6-13-3"/></fig><p>Then we analyzed the effect of treatment with either EGTA or Ca<sup>2+ </sup>on basal cell motility. We found that under control conditions the general morphology of the cells as well as extension of pseudopods was practically identical in both strains (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4 A, B</xref>, [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Additional file 1</xref>]). Preincubation with 10 mM EGTA for 60 min led to strong rounding of wild type and mutant amoebae (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4 C, D</xref>) with reduced extension of small pseudopods [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">Additional file 2</xref>]. By contrast, pretreatment with 10 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>did not affect the morphology (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4 E, F</xref>) or the extension of pseudopods [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">Additional file 3</xref>] in both strains. Next we tested chemotaxis of amoebae towards a cAMP-filled glass capillary. Under control conditions cells of both strains oriented and migrated towards the tip of the capillary (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5 A, B</xref>); the average chemotactic speed was not different between wild type and the mutant strain (10.7 &#x000b1; 2.1 vs. 11.0 &#x000b1; 0.7 &#x003bc;m/min; mean &#x000b1; s.e.m. of 20 wild type and 43 mutant amoebae analyzed in 3 and 4 independent experiments, respectively). Incubation in 10 mM EGTA for 60 min abolished chemotaxis in most of the wild type and the <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>amoebae: small pseudopods were extended randomly and the cells did not approach the capillary tip (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5 C, D</xref>). Only rarely, cells of both strains exhibited an oriented but highly reduced migration towards the cAMP source (3% and 5% of 33 wild type and 19 mutant cells analyzed in 3 independent experiments, respectively). Thus the loss of Ca<sup>2+ </sup>from stores impairs both, orientation and migration also in the absence of the <italic>iplA </italic>gene product. By contrast, when amoebae were incubated in 10 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>for 60 min to load stores, they oriented and migrated towards the cAMP capillary (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5 E, F</xref>). The chemotactic speed of wild type cells (9.9 &#x000b1; 1.2 &#x003bc;m/min; mean &#x000b1; s.e.m. of 17 cells tested in 3 independent experiments) was comparable to that under control conditions whereas mutant amoebae chemotaxed significantly faster (13.6 &#x000b1; 1.7 &#x003bc;m/min; mean &#x000b1; s.e.m. of 15 mutant amoebae analyzed in 3 independent experiments) than wild type cells in the presence of 10 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>(Mann-Whitney rank sum test, p = 0.041).</p><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>General morphology of wild type and <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells under control conditions (A, B), in the presence of 10 mM EGTA for 60 min (C, D) or in the presence of 10 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>for 80 min (E, F). In H5-buffer or in the presence of 10 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>the morphology was not significantly different between wild type and mutant amoebae. However, in the presence of EGTA the cells of both strains were rounded. Photographs were taken at t<sub>5</sub>. Basal motility under these conditions can be viewed in the accompanying movies.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-6-13-4"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Chemotaxis of wild type and mutant amoebae at different experimental conditions. The tracks of individual cells (in red) migrating during chemotactic stimulation (position of the tip of the cAMP-filled capillary: green star) are shown. In H5-buffer (A, B) both cell types migrated in an oriented manner towards the capillary tip, albeit not always in a straight line. After preincubation with 10 mM EGTA for 60 min and in its continued presence during the chemotaxis assay (C, D) the cells remained stationary with random pseudopod extension. Preincubation of amoebae with 10 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>(E, F) did not impair chemotaxis; rather, the cells of both strains migrated towards the capillary tip. Chemotaxis experiments were done at t<sub>6</sub>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-6-13-5"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Buffering of intracellular [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] impairs chemotaxis</title><p>The observation that aggregation occurred in the mutant cell line although a cAMP-activated increase in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i </sub>was not detectable resulted in the conclusion that [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-changes were not necessary to accomplish chemotaxis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. We used the mobile buffer approach originally described by Speksnijder et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>] which allows to analyze the requirement of a [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-gradient for a given response. If in <italic>Dictyostelium </italic>a [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-increase was necessary for chemotaxis, the presence of a Ca<sup>2+</sup>-chelator in the cytosol should impair orientation and/or migration. In a previous study, we had introduced the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-chelator BAPTA and its derivatives into the cytosol of wild type amoebae which indeed had inhibited chemotactic migration and reduced chemotactic orientation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Here we used the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-indicator Fura2-dextran to clamp [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i </sub>and loaded the indicator into wild type and mutant cells in the absence of external CaCl<sub>2</sub>. The treatment affected chemotactic performance of wild type as well as <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>amoebae. Lack of extracellular CaCl<sub>2 </sub>during the loading process induced strong rounding of the amoebae and loss of migration. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> shows that the capacity to orient chemotactically and to extend pseudopods towards the capillary tip was reduced by 58% in wild type (93 cells tested in 4 independent experiments). Inhibition was also evident in <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>) showing sensitivity of the mutant towards buffering of intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup>-levels and eradication of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-changes: the fraction of pseudopods extended in direction of the cAMP-source was reduced by 75% (74 cells tested in 3 independent experiments). These results show that not only in wild type but also in the <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cell line the ability to orient and to migrate in fact depends on an agonist-activated [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-elevation.</p><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Chemotaxis of <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells is impaired in the intracellular presence of a Ca<sup>2+</sup>-buffer. Wild type and mutant amoebae were loaded with Fura2-dextran and their ability to protrude pseudopods towards a cAMP-filled glass capillary was compared to that of untreated cells. In both strains the presence of the chelator in the cytosol led to a decrease in the fraction of cells extending pseudopods and migrating towards the cAMP source.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-6-13-6"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Analysis of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes</title><p>Our findings that differentiation was sensitive towards depletion of Ca<sup>2+ </sup>or loading of the cells with Ca<sup>2+ </sup>and that chemotaxis was blocked by intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup>-buffers led us to investigate Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes in the mutant cell line. We used a Ca<sup>2+</sup>-sensitive electrode in cell suspensions to measure Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes, an approach different from that of Traynor et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] who had studied ion fluxes by <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup>-measurements. First we tested whether the coupling of stores to the plasma membrane, i.e. capacitative Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes without prior stimulation with agonists were altered. In <italic>Dictyostelium </italic>induction of capacitative Ca<sup>2+</sup>-influx requires active intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup>-pumps. Their inhibition by either thapsigargin or 2,5-di-(t-butyl)-1,4-hydroquinone (BHQ) does not evoke influx; rather, stores have to be emptied by treatment with EGTA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Capacitative Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes were studied early during differentiation (t<sub>2</sub>&#x02013;t<sub>4</sub>). At this time Ca<sup>2+</sup>-influx and Ca<sup>2+</sup>-efflux are at an equilibrium which held true for both, wild type and mutant cells (not shown); in suspensions of cells at later stages of development influx strongly exceeds efflux [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. In <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>and in wild type cells emptying of storage compartments via preincubation of amoebae with EGTA induced capacitative Ca<sup>2+</sup>-entry (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7 A</xref>) which was blocked by addition of 1 mM NaN<sub>3 </sub>(Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7 B</xref>). The characteristics of influx were comparable in wild type and mutant cells. These data show that capacitative Ca<sup>2+</sup>-influx does not depend on the product of the <italic>iplA </italic>gene.</p><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Recordings of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes in <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>and wild type amoebae. [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>e </sub>was measured in cell suspensions with a Ca<sup>2+</sup>-sensitive electrode. (A) Treatment of amoebae with 5 mM EGTA for 30 min activated capacitative Ca<sup>2+</sup>-influx (one out of 12/6 determinations in 4/3 independent experiments is shown for <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>and wild type, respectively). (B) Capacitative influx was blocked by the addition of 1 mM NaN<sub>3 </sub>(one out of 5/4 determinations in 3/3 independent experiments). Measurements were done at t<sub>3</sub>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-6-13-7"/></fig><p>On the other hand, agonist-activated <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup>-entry had been reported to be absent in the mutant strain; in their study, Traynor et al. had stimulated cells with cAMP in the presence of 0.1 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. The use of a Ca<sup>2+</sup>-sensitive electrode allows to measure much lower levels of extracellular Ca<sup>2+ </sup>to analyze Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes, in the range of approximately 1 &#x003bc;M Ca<sup>2+</sup>. Indeed, we found that under this condition reversible Ca<sup>2+</sup>-entry occurred after addition of 1 &#x003bc;M cAMP (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8 A</xref>) that amounted to 10.2 &#x000b1; 4.3 pmol Ca<sup>2+</sup>/10<sup>7 </sup>cells (mean &#x000b1; s.d. from 9 experiments). The level of influx represented roughly 5% of wild type influx (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8 B</xref> and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]). Ca<sup>2+</sup>-influx was delayed in the mutant and the time to reach the maximum was longer than in wild type cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. In addition, challenge with arachidonic acid (AA) induced influx (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9 A</xref>). Again, the mutant was less sensitive and higher concentrations were required than those reported to evoke Ca<sup>2+</sup>-entry in wild type cells (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8 B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9 C</xref> and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]). Neither 10 nor 20 &#x003bc;M AA were effective; in the wild type 10 &#x003bc;M AA activates influx of 190 &#x000b1; 58 pmol Ca<sup>2+</sup>/10<sup>7 </sup>cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. At 60 &#x003bc;M AA entry occurred in the mutant strain which amounted to an average of 107 &#x000b1; 21 pmol Ca<sup>2+</sup>/10<sup>7 </sup>cells (mean &#x000b1; s.d. from 7 experiments). Preincubation of cells with the SERCA-type Ca<sup>2+</sup>-ATPase inhibitor BHQ reduced AA-induced influx by 82 % (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9 B</xref>) to an average of 21 &#x000b1; 18 pmol Ca<sup>2+</sup>/10<sup>7 </sup>cells (mean &#x000b1; s.d. from 3 experiments). These data show that Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes across the plasma membrane do occur in <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells as well but at a reduced level.</p><fig position="float" id="F8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Agonist-activated Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes in suspensions of <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>and wild type amoebae. cAMP elicited reversible Ca<sup>2+</sup>-influx in the mutant (A) and in wild type ((B) and see [14]); measurements were done at t<sub>7</sub>&#x02013;t<sub>7.5</sub>. Note the different doses of CaCl<sub>2 </sub>added for calibration. The time points of cAMP-addition (1 &#x003bc;M) and of AA-addition (6 &#x003bc;M) in the wild type are indicated by arrows.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-6-13-8"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F9"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Fatty acids activate Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes in <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>amoebae. (A) 60 &#x003bc;M AA evoked a transient decrease in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>e </sub>representing Ca<sup>2+</sup>-influx; measurement was done at t<sub>6 </sub>(B) After preincubating amoebae with the SERCA-type Ca<sup>2+</sup>-ATPase blocker BHQ (100 &#x003bc;M) for 20 min to inhibit uptake of Ca<sup>2+ </sup>into internal storage compartments, the AA-activated response was absent; measurement was done at t<sub>7.5</sub>. Results of measurements with wild type (C, D) stimulated with 6 &#x003bc;M AA are shown for comparison.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-6-13-9"/></fig><p>Next we tested whether the mutant strain was able to release stored Ca<sup>2+ </sup>when stimulated with cAMP or AA. Fluxes were measured in suspensions of cells with permeabilized plasma membranes; any change in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>e </sub>thus reflects efflux of Ca<sup>2+ </sup>from storage compartments. Both, cAMP and arachidonic acid activated release of stored Ca<sup>2+ </sup>(Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10 A</xref>). On average, addition of 1 &#x003bc;M cAMP released 7.3 &#x000b1; 3.4 pmol Ca<sup>2+</sup>/10<sup>7 </sup>cells and 16.3 &#x000b1; 7.2 pmol Ca<sup>2+</sup>/10<sup>7 </sup>cells were liberated after stimulation with 3 &#x003bc;M AA (mean &#x000b1; s.d. from 10 and 3 experiments, respectively). The amount of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-efflux from stores after cAMP stimulation was 61% of that found in wild type cells (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10 B</xref> and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]) whereas release upon AA-challenge was in the range of 5&#x02013;10% of wild type (see Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]). In addition to the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-electrode recordings, we studied Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes in suspensions of partially purified storage compartments fluorimetrically. ATP induced Ca<sup>2+</sup>-sequestration (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) was of similar magnitude and rate as in wild type stores. This result indicates that the decreased release of Ca<sup>2+ </sup>from the stores measured with the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-electrode is not due to a lack of storage capacity. Moreover, the addition of AA evoked release of Ca<sup>2+ </sup>from stores as did inhibition of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-pump(s) by thapsigargin. XestosponginC that inhibits Ca<sup>2+</sup>-uptake and activates Ca<sup>2+</sup>-release in wild type [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] and the ionophore ionomycin also resulted in substantial Ca<sup>2+ </sup>release in the mutant cell line (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). All values were in the same range as those for wild type.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Determination of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes in partially purified storage compartments of the <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>mutant and of wild type. Ca<sup>2+</sup>-sequestering vesicles were prepared as outlined in Methods. Measurements were performed with the pellet and supernatant fraction. ATP-induced uptake and release activated by different agents is given as nmol Ca<sup>2+</sup>-uptake/min and mg of protein and pmol Ca<sup>2+</sup>-release/tube, respectively (mean &#x000b1; s.d.). In release experiments 60&#x02013;75 &#x003bc;l of pellet and 120&#x02013;140 &#x003bc;l of supernatant fraction were used per tube. Numbers in brackets give number of experiments; n.d.: not determined.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="center" colspan="2"><italic>iplA</italic><sup>-</sup></td><td align="center" colspan="2">Wt</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Stimulation</td><td align="center" colspan="2">Fraction</td><td align="center" colspan="2">Fraction</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Pellet</td><td align="center">Supernatant</td><td align="center">Pellet</td><td align="center">Supernatant</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">Uptake (nmol/min*mg)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">1 mM ATP</td><td align="center">1.96 &#x000b1; 0.55 (4)</td><td align="center">0.28 &#x000b1; 0.15 (4)</td><td align="center">1.87 &#x000b1; 0.74 (3)</td><td align="center">0.38 &#x000b1; 0.16 (3)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Release (pmol/tube)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">10 &#x003bc;M AA</td><td align="center">360 &#x000b1; 227 (8)</td><td align="center">761 &#x000b1; 218 (6)</td><td align="center">396 &#x000b1; 122 (6)</td><td align="center">961 &#x000b1; 374 (2)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">40 &#x003bc;M Thapsigargin</td><td align="center">570 &#x000b1; 250 (6)</td><td align="center">170 &#x000b1; 73 (6)</td><td align="center">582 &#x000b1; 123 (5)</td><td align="center">265 &#x000b1; 135 (2)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">6 &#x003bc;M XestosponginC</td><td align="center">201 &#x000b1; 55 (4)</td><td align="center">n.d.</td><td align="center">276 &#x000b1; 46 (3)</td><td align="center">n.d.</td></tr><tr><td align="center">2 &#x003bc;M Ionomycin</td><td align="center">447 &#x000b1; 147 (5)</td><td align="center">147 &#x000b1; 41 (4)</td><td align="center">580&#x000b1; 173 (3)</td><td align="center">193 &#x000b1; 76 (2)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F10"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>cAMP and arachidonic acid elicit Ca<sup>2+</sup>-release from internal stores. (A) [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>e </sub>was recorded at t<sub>7 </sub>in <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells with permeabilized plasma membranes. Amoebae were challenged with 1 &#x003bc;M cAMP and 3 &#x003bc;M AA, respectively. (B) The response of permeabilized wild type stimulated with 1 &#x003bc;M cAMP at t<sub>6 </sub>is shown for comparison.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-6-13-10"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Mn<sup>2+</sup>-quenching experiments</title><p>The [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>e</sub>-recordings in suspensions of cells as described above detect the sum of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-influx and efflux. Therefore, a complementary approach which monitors influx only was pursued, by using the Mn<sup>2+</sup>-quenching technique in single intact amoebae. This method is based on the fact that many Ca<sup>2+</sup>-channels are permeable to Mn<sup>2+ </sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>] and that the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-indicator Fura2 binds Mn<sup>2+ </sup>with high affinity. Fluorescence of the indicator is quenched upon binding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. We compared quenching of Fura2-dextran fluorescence activated by addition of Mn<sup>2+ </sup>alone or in combination with 1 &#x003bc;M cAMP in wild type and mutant cells. Higher concentrations of MnCl<sub>2 </sub>were required to quench Fura2-dextran fluorescence in <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>amoebae (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Reduction of fluorescence occurred at 1 &#x003bc;M Mn<sup>2+ </sup>and 1 &#x003bc;M Mn<sup>2+</sup>/cAMP in wild type (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11 A, B</xref>; see also [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]) but not in the mutant (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11 C, D</xref>) where addition of 100 &#x003bc;M Mn<sup>2+</sup>/cAMP was necessary; 100 &#x003bc;M Mn<sup>2+ </sup>alone was not effective (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11 C, D</xref>) but started at 200 &#x003bc;M Mn<sup>2+ </sup>(not shown). These data show that the reduction in ion fluxes in the mutant were indeed due to an alteration in entry mechanisms.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Rate of basal and cAMP-induced Mn<sup>2+</sup>-influx. Amoebae were challenged with 1 or 100 &#x003bc;M Mn<sup>2+ </sup>either with or without 1 &#x003bc;M cAMP. Cells were preincubated with 0.1 mM EGTA as outlined in Methods. Mn<sup>2+ </sup>quenching of fura-2-dextran fluorescence was tested in H5-buffer and is expressed as decrease in fluorescence units/sec (mean &#x000b1; s.e.m.). Numbers in brackets give number of cells tested and number of experiments.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">Stimulation</td><td align="center" colspan="2">Preincubation</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">none</td><td align="center">EGTA (0.1 mM)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">1 &#x003bc;M Mn<sup>2+</sup></td><td align="center">0 (121/5)</td><td align="center">0.37 &#x000b1; 0.2 (142/3)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1 &#x003bc;M Mn<sup>2+</sup>/1 &#x003bc;M cAMP</td><td align="center">0 (135/5)</td><td align="center">1.4 &#x000b1; 0.1 (207/4)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">100 &#x003bc;M Mn<sup>2+</sup></td><td align="center">0 (109/3)</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">100 &#x003bc;M Mn<sup>2+</sup>/1 &#x003bc;M cAMP</td><td align="center">1.0 &#x000b1; 0.2 (292/9)</td><td></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F11"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p>Basal and cAMP-induced Mn<sup>2+</sup>-influx. Influx was assayed by quenching of Fura2-dextran fluorescence. (A, B) The response of wild type amoebae is shown for comparison; 1 &#x003bc;M Mn<sup>2+ </sup>&#x000b1; 1 &#x003bc;M cAMP was added. <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells in nominally Ca<sup>2+</sup>-free buffer were challenged with 100 &#x003bc;M Mn<sup>2+ </sup>&#x000b1; 1 &#x003bc;M cAMP at t<sub>7 </sub>(closed symbols); when 1 &#x003bc;M Mn<sup>2+ </sup>was added (open symbols) no influx was detected (C, D). After preincubation with EGTA influx was observed at 1&#x02013;2 &#x003bc;M Mn<sup>2+ </sup>&#x000b1; 1 &#x003bc;M cAMP (E, F). Fluorescence intensity at 360 nm excitation is shown as mean &#x000b1; s.e.m</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-6-13-11"/></fig><p>In principle, the <italic>iplA </italic>gene product could form a channel in the plasma membrane or in membranes of internal stores. The lack of the <italic>iplA </italic>gene product in the stores might impair their coupling to the plasma membrane. As we had observed capacitative Ca<sup>2+</sup>-entry in the mutant we asked whether manipulation of the filling state of the stores altered ion fluxes. First we tested the effect of emptying of stores on Mn<sup>2+</sup>-influx. When cells were preincubated with EGTA, the requirement for high doses of Mn<sup>2+ </sup>to quench fluorescence was abrogated. Now capacitative and also agonist-activated Mn<sup>2+</sup>-influx occurred at concentrations of MnCl<sub>2 </sub>comparable to those used under control conditions in wild type, in the range of 1&#x02013;2 &#x003bc;M (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11 E, F</xref>). This result renders the possibility that the plasma membrane is altered in the mutant unlikely. Yet, the rate of Mn<sup>2+</sup>-influx observed in EGTA-treated mutant amoebae was still less than in wild type cells with respect to both basal and cAMP-activated fluxes (53 and 58% of wild type [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], respectively).</p></sec><sec><title>[Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-determination</title><p>In wild type cells treatment with EGTA augments responsiveness and cAMP-elicited [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-transients are detected at low extracellular [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. However, an agonist-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i </sub>elevation was not observed in <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells under these conditions. On the other hand, when stores were loaded in the continued presence of CaCl<sub>2</sub>, we observed that differentiation of the mutant resembled the wild type as described above. This led us to compare the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-response of wild type and mutant amoebae after pretreatment with CaCl<sub>2</sub>. In wild type cells preincubation with 1 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>for 10&#x02013;15 min and its continued presence during the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-imaging experiment is required to activate a [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-transient after challenge with cAMP (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12 A</xref> and see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]); in nominally Ca<sup>2+</sup>-free medium or at very low extracellular [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] a cAMP-activated [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-elevation is not observed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. In accordance with the data of Traynor et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] this condition (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12 B</xref>) and even increasing the concentration of CaCl<sub>2 </sub>to 20 mM resulted in no detectable [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-increase in the mutant strain (not shown). However, we found that the basal [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i </sub>level in <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>amoebae was significantly lower than in wild type and amounted to an average of 36 &#x000b1; 3 nM (mean &#x000b1; s.e.m. of 8 determinations in 3 independent experiments) as compared to 50 &#x000b1; 2 nM in wild type (mean &#x000b1; s.e.m. of 29 determinations in 9 independent experiments; Mann-Whitney rank sum test, p = 0.002).</p><fig position="float" id="F12"><label>Figure 12</label><caption><p>[Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-recordings in cells preincubated with CaCl<sub>2 </sub>in order to load stores. (A) The response of wild type upon stimulation with 1 &#x003bc;M cAMP (arrow) at standard conditions, i.e. after preincubation with 1 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>for 10&#x02013;15 min and stimulated in the presence of 1 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>is shown. Values give mean &#x000b1; s.e.m. of 7 cells. (B) When <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells were stimulated with 1 &#x003bc;M cAMP at standard conditions (as outlined in (A)), no response was observed. Mean &#x000b1; s.e.m. of 6 cells is shown. (C) Wild type was preincubated with 1 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>for 4&#x02013;5 h; after washing cells were incubated in H5-buffer supplemented with 1 &#x003bc;M CaCl<sub>2 </sub>and challenged with 1 &#x003bc;M cAMP (arrow). Values give mean &#x000b1; s.e.m. of 16 cells. (D) <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>incubated for 3 h with 20 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>were washed and subsequently [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-imaging was done in buffer containing 1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>. Arrow indicates the time point when 1 &#x003bc;M cAMP was added. Mean &#x000b1; s.e.m. of 10 cells is shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-6-13-12"/></fig><p>For stronger loading of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-stores, we preincubated cells with 1 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>for 4 h. After this treatment a [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-elevation upon addition of cAMP was detected in 60% of wild type amoebae even at low extracellular [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] levels, i.e. when the buffer used to wash the cells had been supplemented with only 1 &#x003bc;M CaCl<sub>2 </sub>(Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12 C</xref>). Starting from a basal level of 48 &#x000b1; 4 nM, the height of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-transient amounted to 23 &#x000b1; 2 nM (mean &#x000b1; s.e.m. of 12 determinations in 8 independent experiments). Again, these conditions were not effective in <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells; rather, the sensitivity of the mutant was shifted to higher Ca<sup>2+ </sup>concentrations as had been found with Mn<sup>2+</sup>-quenching experiments. We preincubated <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>amoebae with 20 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>for 3 h; after washing thoroughly, a cAMP-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-elevation in the presence of 1 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>was observed (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12 D</xref>) in 28% of the cells; its average height amounted to 67 &#x000b1; 11 nM (mean &#x000b1; s.e.m. of 15 determinations in 4 independent experiments) starting from a basal level of 39 &#x000b1; 2 nM. In the course of these experiments we once observed a response also under standard conditions, i.e. at 1 mM [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>e </sub>without prior incubation in 20 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>; the height of the increase amounted to 54 &#x000b1; 6 nM (mean &#x000b1; s.e.m.). Yet, this was a rare event (once in 31 determinations).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>The role of cAMP-activated [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-changes for chemotaxis has been questioned by Traynor et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] who reported results obtained with the <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>mutant cell line favouring insignificance of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i </sub>for the chemotactic response. The authors had observed formation of fruiting bodies even though neither <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes nor an agonist induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-elevation were detectable. The discrepancy between our view that a [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-elevation is necessary for a proper chemotactic response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] and the conclusion of Traynor et al. prompted us to analyze chemotaxis, differentiation and the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]-regulation of the <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>mutant in detail. In particular, we tested not only basal and cAMP-activated ion fluxes but also capacitative Ca<sup>2+</sup>-entry which is induced by emptying internal Ca<sup>2+</sup>-stores via preincubation of amoebae with EGTA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>].</p><p>Aggregation and development of wild type and mutant cells on agar plates was sensitive towards continuous emptying or loading of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-stores. These effects are not necessarily caused by altering chemotactic migration. It is conceivable that other Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent processes were affected, e.g. that the timing or pattern of gene expression or the establishment of cell contacts was altered. Although incubation of mutant amoebae for 2 h with 20 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>or of wild type with 1 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>for 4&#x02013;5 h or with 1 mM EGTA for 1 h [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>] did not significantly increase or lower basal [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i </sub>it is possible that the continued presence of 10 mM EGTA or CaCl<sub>2 </sub>for many hours affects basal levels of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i </sub>which in turn might mediate effects on gene expression as was shown for prolonged incubation of cells with BHQ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. During development <italic>Dictyostelium </italic>cells form Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent and EDTA/EGTA-sensitive cell-cell contacts that are mediated by gp24 and DdCAD-1 ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]; for review see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]). Therefore, chelation of extracellular Ca<sup>2+ </sup>might also inhibit cell adhesion. However, mutant cells whose gene encoding DdCAD-1 had been disrupted show normal chemotaxis and cell streams. Furthermore, mound formation was accelerated and only culmination was delayed by about 6 hours [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. If only Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent cell adhesion was affected in our development assay in the presence of EGTA we would expect a similar phenotype. However, aggregation was clearly delayed. This argues for additional Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent processes during aggregation.</p><p>When we tested the influence of the presence of EGTA or CaCl<sub>2 </sub>on spontaneous motility and chemotaxis we found that in both strains motility in general was strongly impaired and that chemotaxis of the amoebae towards the cAMP-filled glass capillary was virtually abolished upon depletion of internal stores by the extracellular presence of EGTA. This effect is time dependent; after 30 min of incubation with 10 mM EGTA the behaviour of wild type amoebae was found to be unaltered and only after treatment for 0.5&#x02013;1 h rounding and reduction of pseudopod elongation towards the capillary tip occurred [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Prolonged incubation for more than 1 h as carried out in this study completely inhibited the chemotactic response. These results strengthen the view that Ca<sup>2+ </sup>has a necessary role in chemotaxis in wild type and in the mutant as well. When the cellular Ca<sup>2+ </sup>content falls below a critical value Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent cytoskeletal rearrangements [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>] that are necessary for both, random pseudopod extension during spontaneous motility and oriented pseudopod formation after chemotactic stimulation no longer take place correctly. On the other hand, the presence of 10 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>induced no alteration of basal cell motility in wild type or mutant amoebae. Yet, during chemotactic stimulation the average speed of migration towards the capillary tip was higher in mutant than in wild type cells. In this respect it is of importance that the basal level of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i </sub>was significantly lower in the former. At standard conditions the reduced basal [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i </sub>does not impair the capacity of the mutant to chemotax. Therefore, this particular mutant strain represents the "minimal solution" with respect to the concentration of cytosolic Ca<sup>2+ </sup>necessary to accomplish cytoskeletal rearrangements and extrusion of a pseudopod correctly. However, in the presence of 10 mM extracellular Ca<sup>2+ </sup>during cAMP-stimulation Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes are enhanced allowing more efficient formation of pseudopods. We had shown previously that a small global elevation of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i </sub>activates the extension of pseudopods all over the cell's circumference whereas a larger increase induces contraction of the amoebae [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. In our view, the strongest evidence that a [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-transient is necessary for the extension of pseudopods rests upon the experiment where a Ca<sup>2+</sup>-chelator was introduced into the cytosol of the amoebae. This treatment led to rounding of the amoebae and a general reduction of pseudopod formation (see also [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]). Upon stimulation with a cAMP-filled capillary, the extension of oriented pseudopods was greatly reduced and migration towards the capillary tip was abolished. As Speksnijder et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>] had pointed out the fact that the presence of a chelator has an effect shows that a [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-gradient is essential for a given response. In summary, these data support the notion that an elevation of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i </sub>is required to extend pseudopods; suppression of the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-elevation inhibits motility in general. Upon chemotactic challenge with cAMP this [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-gradient has to be established in a locally restricted fashion in order to allow local, oriented pseudopod formation (see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]); otherwise pseudopods would be extended in all directions (see above, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]). Our results imply that in <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells such a [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-gradient occurs as well, either nonrestricted allowing extension of pseudopods at random sites during spontaneous motility or restricted locally after chemotactic stimulation leading to oriented pseudopod formation. The fact that in the mutant cell line cAMP-activated [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-changes were practically undetectable under our standard condition argue for a [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-increase that is either smaller and/or more restricted to distinct domains within the cell than in wild type amoebae. Indeed, in only one out of roughly 30 determinations did we observe a cAMP-activated [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-transient under standard conditions. These results imply a crucial role but not an absolute necessity of the <italic>iplA </italic>gene product for the regulation of cAMP-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-changes.</p><p>By using a Ca<sup>2+</sup>-sensitive electrode in cell suspensions, we analyzed which aspects of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i </sub>are controlled by the <italic>iplA </italic>gene product. Besides studying agonist-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes we also investigated capacitative Ca<sup>2+</sup>-entry and found that this type of influx was similar in mutant and wild type cell suspensions. We obtained equivalent results by testing Mn<sup>2+</sup>-quenching of Fura2-dextran fluorescence which showed that capacitative entry is independent of the <italic>iplA </italic>gene product.</p><p>On the other hand, using the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-sensitive electrode, we found that in the <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>mutant the agonist cAMP and also AA did activate Ca<sup>2+</sup>-entry into intact cells. The difference between the data published by Traynor et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] and our results is most likely due to the experimental conditions: the magnitude of the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes that we observed was considerably lower than in wild type cells and detectable at low extracellular [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] only. The <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+</sup>-flux studies had been performed at 100 &#x003bc;M external CaCl<sub>2</sub>; so the fraction of <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2+ </sup>entering the cells was presumably too low to be detected reliably. Moreover, we found cAMP- and AA-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup>-release from stores in cells with permeabilized plasma membranes. These data show that cAMP-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup>-release from stores in <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells is functional. However, much like the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-influx, agonist-activated liberation from stores was smaller than in wild type amoebae. In line with these results are the findings using Mn<sup>2+</sup>-quenching to assay ion fluxes in intact single cells: higher doses of Mn<sup>2+ </sup>were necessary to detect influx.</p><p>There are several interpretations for the results above. (i) There are two types of channels responsible for Ca<sup>2+</sup>-influx: one type being activated by emptying of the stores and sustaining capacitative Ca<sup>2+</sup>-entry which is unaffected in <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells and the other one mediating agonist-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes, the latter being under the control of the <italic>iplA </italic>gene product. The view that there are two strictly separated ion channels seems unlikely as under conditions of emptied stores cAMP-activated Mn<sup>2+</sup>-quenching occurred in the mutant as well. (ii) The same channel(s) mediate capacitative and agonist-activated fluxes but upon stimulation with agonists it cannot be addressed properly when <italic>iplA </italic>is disrupted. This implies a role of the protein in the liberation of Ca<sup>2+ </sup>from the stores which is a prerequisite for the triggering of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-entry [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. In the mutant this cannot proceed normally so subsequent activation of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-influx and the generation of a full [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-increase is impaired. The results of the experiments where stores were strongly loaded with Ca<sup>2+ </sup>prior to stimulation support this notion. In this situation release from stores should be augmented. Indeed, in both, wild type and mutant cells, cAMP-activated [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-elevations occurred at an extracellular [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] (see Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12</xref>) where without pretreatment no increase was observed. Presumably, release of Ca<sup>2+ </sup>from the filled stores contributed to the observed [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-increase to a greater extent than under standard conditions. The requirement for 20 fold higher concentrations of CaCl<sub>2 </sub>during preincubation to elicit an agonist-induced [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-elevation in <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells are most likely due to the reduction in Ca<sup>2+</sup>-entry which necessitates a higher concentration gradient across the plasma membrane to fill the stores efficiently.</p><p>An as yet unresolved issue is the mechanism that induces Ca<sup>2+</sup>-entry upon liberation of Ca<sup>2+ </sup>from the stores. From our data we conclude that in <italic>Dictyostelium </italic>these signals are different when the stores are emptied by EGTA or by agonist-activated signaling cascades. Otherwise one cannot explain normal capacitative Ca<sup>2+</sup>- and Mn<sup>2+</sup>-influx induced by EGTA-treatment and a requirement for 100 fold higher ion concentrations to induce Mn<sup>2+</sup>-entry by cAMP. If indeed the <italic>iplA </italic>gene product constitutes an IP<sub>3</sub>-receptor like channel that is located on membranes of stores the physical coupling of the receptor to channels in the plasma membrane as a mechanism to activate extracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup>-entry [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>] should be missing in the mutant. On the other hand, emptying of stores by EGTA-treatment influences not only the IP<sub>3</sub>-sensitive store but also other stores and thus exerts a much more general effect on the cells. Studies using microarrays should reveal whether the expression of other genes is affected by the absence of <italic>iplA </italic>and thus might give a clue how [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i </sub>is regulated in the mutant although one type of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-store is malfunctional.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our results show that Ca<sup>2+ </sup>fluxes and regulation of Ca<sup>2+ </sup>homeostasis take place in the <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>mutant and that chemotaxis and development of the mutant are sensitive to disturbance of the Ca<sup>2+ </sup>homeostasis. In wild type cells and in cells lacking the <italic>iplA </italic>gene changes in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i </sub>are necessary to orient and to migrate chemotactically; their abolition causes loss of chemotaxis towards a cAMP source. The <italic>iplA </italic>gene product exerts a crucial role in the control of basal [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i </sub>and of agonist induced Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes. It is not required to activate capacitative Ca<sup>2+</sup>-influx. Thus the mechanisms responsible for capacitative and agonist-activated Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes are different.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec sec-type="materials"><title>Materials</title><p>Fura2-dextran and Fura2 were purchased from MobiTec; cAMP was from Boehringer.</p></sec><sec><title>Cell culture</title><p><italic>D. discoideum </italic>wild type strain Ax2 and the <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cell lines HM1049 and HM1038 (kindly provided by Dr. D. Traynor) were cultured as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] in the absence or presence of 10 &#x003bc;g/ml Blasticidin S, respectively. There was no difference between the two mutant strains with respect to the assays performed; therefore, results of measurements with either HM1038 or HM1049 are shown. Cells were washed by repeated centrifugation and resuspension in cold S&#x000f8;rensen phosphate buffer (17 mM Na<sup>+</sup>/K<sup>+</sup>-phosphate, pH 6.0). Amoebae were shaken at 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7 </sup>cells/ml, 150 rpm and 23&#x000b0;C until use. The time, in hours, after induction of development is designated t<sub>x</sub>.</p></sec><sec><title>[Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>e</sub>-electrode recordings</title><p>[Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>e </sub>in cell suspensions was recorded as described elsewhere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Cells at t<sub>5</sub>&#x02013;t<sub>8 </sub>were washed by repeated centrifugation and resupended at 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7 </sup>cells/ml in 5 mM Tricine, 5 mM KCl, pH 7.0. Permeabilization was done by addition of filipin (15 &#x003bc;g/ml) to cell suspensions exactly as outlined in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Capacitative Ca<sup>2+</sup>-influx was analyzed in cells with emptied storage compartments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]: amoebae at t<sub>2</sub>&#x02013;t<sub>4 </sub>were incubated with 5 mM EGTA for 30 min before washing in the above buffer.</p></sec><sec><title>[Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-determination and Mn<sup>2+</sup>-quenching experiments</title><p>Cells were loaded with Fura2-dextran (5 mg/ml + 1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>) at t<sub>4</sub>&#x02013;t<sub>5 </sub>as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Aliquots (2&#x02013;5 &#x003bc;l) of washed cells in H5-buffer (5 mM Hepes, 5 mM KCl, pH 7.0) were placed on glass coverslips and incubated in a humid chamber. 10&#x02013;15 min prior to the experiment, 85&#x02013;88 &#x003bc;l of H5-buffer + 1 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>were added. In a series of experiments to load stores, wild type and <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells were incubated with 1 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>for 4&#x02013;5 h and with 20 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>for 2&#x02013;3 h, respectively. Then they were thoroughly washed exactly as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>] and incubated either in H5-buffer supplemented with 1 &#x003bc;M CaCl<sub>2 </sub>(wild type; free [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] in the solution was measured to be 2&#x02013;2.5 &#x003bc;M, see also [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]) or in H5-buffer +1 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>(<italic>iplA</italic><sup>-</sup>); final volume was 90 &#x003bc;l. Single cell [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>-imaging was performed at t<sub>7</sub>&#x02013;t<sub>8 </sub>as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]; stimulation was done by adding 10 &#x003bc;l of cAMP (10 &#x003bc;M). For Mn<sup>2+</sup>-quenching assays, washed cells were incubated in H5-buffer and challenged with Mn<sup>2+ </sup>or Mn<sup>2+</sup>/cAMP. In order to study fluxes in cells with partially emptied internal storage compartments cells were preincubated with EGTA (10 &#x003bc;l of H5-buffer plus 0.1 mM EGTA for 1&#x02013;2 h). 10&#x02013;15 min prior to the experiment this solution was carefully removed and 100 &#x003bc;l of H5-buffer was added. This was repeated three times; final volume was 90 &#x003bc;l. Fluorescence quenching was measured at 360 nm excitation; influx rates are given as decrease of fluorescence units/sec.</p></sec><sec><title>Measurement of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes in partially purified storage compartments</title><p>Analysis of vesicular Ca<sup>2+</sup>-fluxes was done as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. In brief, 3 ml of cells at t<sub>1</sub>&#x02013;t<sub>6 </sub>(2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>8 </sup>cells/ml) in 20 mM Hepes, pH 7.2, were lysed by passage through Nuclepore filters. A final concentration of 3 % sucrose, 50 mM KCl, 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 20 &#x003bc;g/ml leupeptin, 1 &#x003bc;g/&#x003bc;l aprotinin, 2.5 mM dithiothreitol and 1 &#x003bc;M microcystin were added; unbroken cells were removed by centrifugation at 3000 g for 5 min. The supernatant was centrifuged again at 12000 g for 20 min. The sediment (P) was resuspended in 1 ml of the above buffer. The rate of uptake and release was determined in the pellet and supernatant fraction by measuring the extravesicular [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] with Fura2.</p></sec><sec><title>Chemotaxis assays</title><p>Cells were analyzed for chemotaxis towards a capillary filled with 0.1 mM cAMP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. 250 &#x003bc;l of 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5 </sup>cells/ml in H5-buffer were pipetted onto a glass coverslip and allowed to settle for 60 min. Chemotaxis was recorded on a video recorder for 30&#x02013;45 min. Chemotaxis was also assayed in the presence of EGTA or CaCl<sub>2</sub>; then amoebae were incubated in the respective agents for 60 min before they were challenged with cAMP. Images were digitized and the behaviour of the cells was analyzed using a computer program written for this purpose. For determination of cell velocity, a square area of interest (AI) of variable size (usually roughly 1/3 of the area of the cell) was placed at the perimeter of the cell in the first image digitized at the beginning of the assay. In the next image (images were digitized at a 2&#x02013;4 sec time interval) the program analyzed an area larger than the AI (this area was defined by adding a given number of pixels on each side of the AI) for a pattern that resembled that of the AI; when such a pattern was found then the AI was placed on this new spot. The difference between the position of the AI in the first image to that in the second image was expressed as a vector of a given length. The changes in cell shape during migration were compensated by updating the pattern within the AI for every consecutive image analyzed. Calibration of the system allowed to convert the sum of the vector lengths to the distance in &#x003bc;m that the cells had migrated at the end of the experiment and to calculate the velocity of the amoebae. To test the effect of the intracellular presence of a Ca<sup>2+</sup>-buffer on chemotaxis, cells were loaded with Fura2-dextran (5 mg/ml in the loading solution) by electroporation in the absence of added external Ca<sup>2+</sup>. The amount of indicator present in the cytosol is in the range of 2&#x02013;5% of the concentration present during electroporation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. 20 min after loading, cells were stimulated for 3&#x02013;4 min by placing the cAMP-filled glass capillary at a distance of 10&#x02013;20 &#x003bc;m of the cells and the number of cells that extended oriented pseudopods and thus elongated towards the capillary tip within this time period was counted. We had shown previously that loading of amoebae with FITC-dextran as a control does not alter chemotaxis as compared to untreated cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Analysis of differentiation</title><p>Time lapse recordings of the development of Ax2 and <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells on 1.5 % agar in H5-buffer (H5-agar) were done by placing 4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6 </sup>cells each on one half of a petri dish (&#x02205; 35 mm) at t<sub>1</sub>. The two populations were separated from each other by a thin plastic disc that had been inserted in the melted agar during cooling. Only after removal of fluid and slight drying of the plate the disc was removed which resulted in a thin rim separating the strains. Differentiation was recorded by capturing an image of the plate every 30 min using a stereo microscope (Stemi 2000, Zeiss) equipped with a CCD camera (AVT Horn) under the control of the AxioVision software package (Zeiss). In addition, development was assessed at various levels of extracellular CaCl<sub>2</sub>. Then H5-agar contained either 5&#x02013;20 mM EGTA or 5&#x02013;20 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>List of abbreviations</title><p>Cytosolic free Ca<sup>2+ </sup>concentration: [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub></p><p>2,5-di-(t-butyl)-1,4-hydroquinone: BHQ</p><p>Arachidonic acid: AA</p><p>Area of interest: AI</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>RS recorded extracellular [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] in cell suspensions and participated in the design of the study. DFL participated in the recordings of extracellular [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] and the design of the study. KBR analyzed chemotaxis and differentiation of wild type and mutant cells. KH performed [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i </sub>measurements. DM analyzed fluxes in partially purified storage compartments and was involved in the design of the study. CS participated in [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i </sub>measurements, did Mn<sup>2+</sup>-flux studies, participated in the design of the study and wrote the manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional File 1</title><p>Spontaneous cell motility of wild type and <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>cells in H5-buffer. Images of cells at t<sub>5 </sub>were captured every 15 sec for 20 min.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2121-6-13-S1.mov" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="quicktime"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2"><caption><title>Additional File 2</title><p>Basal cell motility after preincubation of wild type and mutant amoebae with 10 mM EGTA for 60 min (t<sub>4</sub>&#x02013;t<sub>5</sub>). Images of cells at t<sub>5 </sub>were captured every 15 sec for 20 min in the continued presence of EGTA. Cells were rounded and extended smaller pseudopods than under control conditions.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2121-6-13-S2.mov" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="quicktime"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S3"><caption><title>Additional File 3</title><p>Cell motility of wild type and mutant cells after preincubation with 10 mM CaCl<sub>2 </sub>for 80 min (t<sub>4</sub>&#x02013;t<sub>5.3</sub>) is shown. Images of cells at t<sub>5.3 </sub>were captured every 15 sec for 20 min in the continued presence of CaCl<sub>2</sub>. The behaviour of treated cells was not different from control amoebae.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2121-6-13-S3.mov" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="quicktime"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors wish to thank Dr. D. Traynor and Prof. R. Kay for generously providing the <italic>iplA</italic><sup>- </sup>strain and Rupert Mutzel and Gerd Knoll for many helpful discussions and critical reading of the manuscript. We are indebted to Georg Heine and Williams Pascual from the Wissenschaftliche Werkst&#x000e4;tten of the University of Konstanz for computer programming and to Katja Drews, Cyrus Nassiri and Frank Zucchetti for performing initial Ca<sup>2+</sup>-electrode measurements. This work was supported by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bumann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wurster</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Malchow</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Attractant induced changes and oscillations of the extracellular Ca++ concentration in suspensions of differentiating Dictyostelium cells</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1984</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6323484</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.98.1.173</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yumura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Furuya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intracellular free calcium responses during chemotaxis of Dictyostelium cells</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>1996</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>2673</fpage><lpage>2678</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8937985</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nebl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intracellular Ca2+ signals in Dictyostelium chemotaxis are mediated exclusively by Ca2+ influx</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>1997</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>2845</fpage><lpage>2853</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9427292</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sonnemann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Aichem</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlatterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dissection of the cAMP induced cytosolic calcium response in Dictyostelium discoideum: the role of cAMP receptor subtypes and G protein subunits</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>1998</year><volume>436</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9781694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-5793(98)01139-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Unterweger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlatterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Introduction of calcium buffers into the cytosol of Dictyostelium discoideum amoebae alters cell morphology and inhibits chemotaxis</article-title><source>Cell Calcium</source><year>1995</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7736566</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0143-4160(95)90079-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Traynor</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Milne</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Insall</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ca2+ signalling is not required for chemotaxis in Dictyostelium</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2000</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>4846</fpage><lpage>4854</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10970875</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/19.17.4846</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miyamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Izumi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Karaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Xestospongin C, a selective and membrane-permeable inhibitor of IP3 receptor, attenuates the positive inotropic effect of alpha-adrenergic stimulation in guinea-pig papillary muscle</article-title><source>Br J Pharmacol</source><year>2000</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>650</fpage><lpage>654</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10821794</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bjp.0703358</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schaloske</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlatterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Malchow</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Xestospongin C-sensitive Ca2+ store is required for cAMP-induced Ca2+-influx and cAMP-oscillations in Dictyostelium</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>8404</fpage><lpage>8408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10722673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.275.12.8404</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Europe-Finner</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>McClue</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Newell</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of aggregation in Dictyostelium by EGTA-induced depletion of calcium</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>1984</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16948639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-1097(84)90172-1</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlatterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Buravkov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zierold</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Knoll</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Calcium-sequestering organelles of Dictyostelium discoideum: changes in element content during early development as measured by electron probe X-ray microanalysis</article-title><source>Cell Calcium</source><year>1994</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7982261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0143-4160(94)90005-1</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Speksnijder</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisenseel</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaffe</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Calcium buffer injections block fucoid egg development by facilitating calcium diffusion</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1989</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>6607</fpage><lpage>6611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2505254</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlatterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Happle</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lusche</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnemann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytosolic [Ca2+]-transients in Dictyostelium discoideum depend on the filling state of internal stores and on an active SERCA Ca2+-pump</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>18407</fpage><lpage>18414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14973132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M307096200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schaloske</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Malchow</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanism of cAMP-induced Ca2+-influx in Dictyostelium: the role of phospholipase A2</article-title><source>Biochem J</source><year>1997</year><volume>327</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9355757</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schaloske</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnemann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Malchow</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlatterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fatty acids induce release of Ca2+ from acidosomal stores and activate capacitative Ca2+-entry in Dictyostelium discoideum</article-title><source>Biochem J</source><year>1998</year><volume>332</volume><fpage>541</fpage><lpage>548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9601085</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flaadt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaworski</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlatterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Malchow</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cyclic AMP- and Ins(1,4,5)P3- induced Ca2+-fluxes in permeabilised cells of Dictyostelium discoideum: cGMP regulates Ca2+ entry across the plasma membrane</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>1993</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>261</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parekh</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Penner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Store depletion and calcium influx</article-title><source>Physiol Rev</source><year>1997</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>901</fpage><lpage>930</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9354808</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grynkiewicz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Poenie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsien</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new generation of Ca2+ indicators with greatly improved fluorescence properties</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1985</year><volume>260</volume><fpage>3440</fpage><lpage>3450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3838314</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schaap</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nebl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A slow sustained increase in cytosolic Ca2+ levels mediates stalk gene induction by differentiation inducing factor in Dictyostelium</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1996</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>5177</fpage><lpage>5183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8895562</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brar</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Siu</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the cell adhesion molecule gp24 in Dictyostelium discoideum. Mediation of cell-cell adhesion via a Ca2+-dependent mechanism</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1993</year><volume>268</volume><fpage>24902</fpage><lpage>24909</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8227052</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Loomis</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Siu</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disruption of the gene encoding the cell adhesion molecule DdCAD-1 leads to aberrant cell sorting and cell-type proportioning during Dictyostelium development</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2002</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>3839</fpage><lpage>3850</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12135922</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siu</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of cell-cell adhesion during Dictyostelium development</article-title><source>Semin Cell Dev Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>633</fpage><lpage>641</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15561583</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.semcdb.2004.09.004</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schleicher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Eichinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Witke</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Noegel</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ca2+-binding proteins as components of the cytoskeleton</article-title><source>Adv Exp Med Biol</source><year>1990</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2191567</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Furukawa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Maselli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Stokes</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Fechheimer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Calcium regulation of actin crosslinking is important for function of the actin cytoskeleton in Dictyostelium</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12456728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.00220</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlatterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaloske</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Calmidazolium leads to an increase in the cytosolic Ca2+ concentration in Dictyostelium discoideum by induction of Ca2+ release from intracellular stores and influx of extracellular Ca2+</article-title><source>Biochem J</source><year>1996</year><volume>313</volume><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>667</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8573107</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malchow</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000f6;hme</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gras</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the role of calcium in chemotaxis and oscillations of Dictyostelium cells</article-title><source>Biophys Struct Mech</source><year>1982</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17557409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00539112</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlatterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gollnick</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Knoll</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Challenge with high concentrations of cyclic AMP induces transient changes in the cytosolic free calcium concentration in Dictyostelium discoideum</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>1994</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>2107</fpage><lpage>2115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7983172</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berridge</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conformational coupling: a physiological calcium entry mechanism</article-title><source>Science STKE</source><year>2004</year><volume>2004</volume><fpage>pe33</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/stke.2432004pe33</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlatterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Malchow</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intracellular Guanosine-5&#x000b4;-O-(3-thiotriphosphate) blocks chemotactic motility of Dictyostelium discoideum amoebae</article-title><source>Cell Motil Cytoskel</source><year>1993</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>298</fpage><lpage>307</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cm.970250309</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sonnemann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Knoll</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlatterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>cAMP-induced changes in the cytosolic free Ca2+ concentration in Dictyostelium discoideum are light sensitive</article-title><source>Cell Calcium</source><year>1997</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9232353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0143-4160(97)90090-7</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



