<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Curr Control Trials Cardiovasc Med</journal-id><journal-title>Current Controlled Trials in Cardiovascular Medicine</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1468-6708</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1468-6694</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15733325</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC553988</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1468-6708-6-2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1468-6708-6-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Presence of factors that activate platelet aggregation in mitral stenotic patients' plasma</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tengiz</surname><given-names>Istemihan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>dritengiz@yahoo.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ercan</surname><given-names>Ertugrul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>ertugrulercan@yahoo.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sahin</surname><given-names>Fahri</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>fsahin@med.ege.edu.tr</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alioglu</surname><given-names>Emin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>emilaliyev@mynet.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Duman</surname><given-names>Can</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>canduman71@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A6" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saydam</surname><given-names>Guray</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>gsaydam@med.ege.edu.tr</email></contrib><contrib id="A7" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Buyukkececi</surname><given-names>Filiz</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>fbuyukkececi@med.ege.edu.tr</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Cardiology, Central Hospital, 1644 sk. No:2/2, 35010 Bayrakli, Izmir, Turkey</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Hematology, Ege University Medical School, 35100 Bornova, Izmir, Turkey</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of Biochemistry, Kocaeli University Medical School, 41900 Derince, Kocaeli, Turkey</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cvm.controlled-trials.com/content/6/1/2"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Tengiz et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Tengiz et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Tengiz
               Istemihan
               
               dritengiz@yahoo.com
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Presence of factors that activate platelet aggregation in mitral stenotic patients' plasma
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Current Controlled Trials in Cardiovascular Medicine 6(1): 2-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1468-6708(2005)6:1&#x0003c;2&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1468-6708</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Although the association between mitral stenosis (MS) and increased coagulation activity is well recognized, it is unclear whether enhanced coagulation remains localized in the left atrium or whether this represents a systemic problem. To assess systemic coagulation parameters and changes in platelet aggregation, we measured fibrinogen levels and performed <italic>in vitro </italic>platelet function tests in plasma obtained from mitral stenotic patients' and from healthy control subjects' peripheral venous blood.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>Sixteen newly diagnosed patients with rheumatic MS (Group P) and 16 healthy subjects (Group N) were enrolled in the study. Platelet-equalized plasma samples were evaluated to determine <italic>in vitro </italic>platelet function, using adenosine diphosphate (ADP), collagen and epinephrine in an automated aggregometer. <italic>In vitro </italic>platelet function tests in group N were performed twice, with and without plasma obtained from group P.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>There were no significant differences between the groups with respect to demographic variables. Peripheral venous fibrinogen levels in Group P were not significantly different from those in Group N. Adenosine diphosphate, epinephrine and collagen-induced platelet aggregation ratios were significantly higher in Group P than in Group N. When plasma obtained from Group P was added to Group N subjects' platelets, ADP and collagen-induced, but not epinephrine-induced, aggregation ratios were significantly increased compared to baseline levels in Group N.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Platelet aggregation is increased in patients with MS, while fibrinogen levels remain similar to controls. We conclude that mitral stenotic patients exhibit increased systemic coagulation activity and that plasma extracted from these patients may contain some transferable factors that activate platelet aggregation.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Systemic thromboembolism represents a major complication in patients with mitral stenosis (MS), especially in those who have atrial fibrillation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. A hypercoagulable state has been reported in patients with MS and sinus rhythm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. The association between MS and higher levels of coagulation is well-known; however, the source of increased coagulation remains unclear. Increased regional left atrial coagulation activity may be involved, even when systemic coagulation assessed by peripheral blood sampling is normal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Others have reported no significant variation in thrombogenesis, platelet activation, and endothelial dysfunction between the left atrium, right atrium and peripheral arteries or veins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>].</p><p>This study assessed systemic coagulation and platelet activities by measuring fibrinogen levels and platelet aggregation in mitral stenotic patients' peripheral venous blood and compared these measures to hematologic parameters in normal controls.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Study groups</title><p>Eighteen newly diagnosed patients with rheumatic MS were enrolled in the study. All were coded as having NYHA class I functional capacities. Two patients were excluded from this study, one due to pregnancy, the second due to current use of oral contraceptives. The study group thus consisted of 16 patients with MS (Group P, 14 female, 2 male, mean age 27.8 &#x000b1; 6.5 years). Peripheral venous coagulation activity and platelet activation tests were also evaluated in 16 control patients (Group N, 13 female, 3 male, mean age 28.3 &#x000b1; 6.1 years), who were normal volunteers. All participants gave informed consent.</p></sec><sec><title>Exclusion criteria</title><p>Patients were excluded from participating in the study for the following reasons: aortic and/or pulmonary valve disease, severe mitral regurgitation and/or left ventricular systolic dysfunction, atrial fibrillation, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, dyslipidemia, a history of renal or liver disease, malignancy, venous thrombosis, systemic or pulmonary embolism, congenital hemorrhagic disease, thrombocytopenia, thrombocytosis, acute or chronic inflammatory disease, autoimmune disease or current use of oral contraceptives or anticoagulant or anti-platelet drugs.</p></sec><sec><title>Echocardiography</title><p>In patients with MS, transthoracic echocardiography was performed with a 2.5-MHz transducer and a Hewlett Packard Sonos 4500 system to assess left atrial (LA) diameter, mitral valve area (MVA) and the transmitral mean pressure gradient (TMmPG). The LA anteroposterior diameter was determined using standard M-mode criteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>], and mitral valve area was calculated according to the pressure half-time method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Fibrinogen measurement</title><p>Peripheral venous blood (for measurement of fibrinogen levels) was transferred into tubes containing 1:9 trisodium citrate (0.109 M, 3.2%). Blood samples were centrifuged within 1 hour of collection at 2,500 g for 10 minutes to separate out the plasma. An STA fibrinogen kit measured fibrinogen levels in plasma, using the clotting method of Clauss. The median inter-assay and intra-assay coefficients of variation for the assays were 3.57% and 3.65% for fibrinogen, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Platelet activation tests</title><p>Blood samples were obtained from the forearm veins of participants, using standard blood drawing procedures (normal blood flow and no pressure). Several samples were drawn for different components of the study. Nine milliliters of blood was collected into special tubes containing 1 ml of 3.8% sodium citrate. Platelet count and other parameters, including white blood cell count and hemoglobin, were measured at the Ege University Hospital Hematology Laboratory using an automated hemocytometer (Cell Dyne 4000 Abbott, USA). Patients with platelet counts less than 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>/ml were excluded from the study. For <italic>in vitro </italic>platelet aggregation tests, platelet-rich plasma (PRP) samples were obtained by centrifuging samples at 1,100 rpm for 10 minutes in a refrigerated centrifuge (Hettich EBA 12R, Germany). Centrifuging samples at 3,000 rpm for 10 minutes yielded platelet-poor plasma (PPP) samples. The platelet counts of both PRP and PPP samples were performed using the same hemocytometer. Platelet-poor plasma samples were added to the PRP samples to obtain a total platelet count of 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>/ml. These platelet-equalized plasma (PEP) samples were analyzed to determine <italic>in vitro </italic>platelet function, using ADP, Collagen and Epinephrine (all from Bio/Data Corp. Horshram, Germany) in an automated aggregometer (Bio/Data Corp. Platelet Agregation Profiler, Horshram-Germany). Results were evaluated and calculated using maximum aggregation ratios.</p><p>PRP from healthy controls was centrifuged for 10 minutes, after which the supernatant was decanted, and normal saline added to the platelet fraction and centrifuged for 10 minutes. This procedure was repeated three times. Plasma obtained from patients with MS was added to the PPP from the control group, and platelet function tests were performed, using the same procedures mentioned above.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>Chi Square tests were employed to compare categorical variables, while Mann Whitney U tests were used, where appropriate, in the univariate analysis. Platelet aggregation changes were evaluated by repeated-measures analysis of variance for intra-group comparisons. Values of p &#x0003c; 0.05 were considered significant. SPSS 10.0 Statistical software was used in the statistical analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>There were no significant differences between Groups P and N for the following variables: age, gender, current smoker, platelet, white blood cell and hemoglobin count. Clinical characteristics of the study groups are shown in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. The peripheral venous fibrinogen levels in patients with MS (301.9 &#x000b1; 53.7 mg/dL) were not significantly different from those in control subjects (284.6 &#x000b1; 55.7 mg/dL).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Clinical features of the study groups and echocardiographic findings of patients with mitral stenosis.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="center"><bold>Group P (n = 16)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Group N (n = 16)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>p</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>Mean age (yrs)</bold></td><td align="center">27.8 &#x000b1; 6.5</td><td align="center">28.3 &#x000b1; 6.1</td><td align="center">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Male/female (n)</bold></td><td align="center">2/14</td><td align="center">3/13</td><td align="center">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Current smoker (n)</bold></td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Platelet count &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup>/mm<sup>3</sup></bold></td><td align="center">253.1 &#x000b1; 33.5</td><td align="center">245.6 &#x000b1; 34.3</td><td align="center">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>WBC/mm<sup>3</sup></bold></td><td align="center">5706 &#x000b1; 1266</td><td align="center">5643 &#x000b1; 1229</td><td align="center">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Hb (g/L)</bold></td><td align="center">12.4 &#x000b1; 1.26</td><td align="center">12.8 &#x000b1; 1.22</td><td align="center">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Fibrinogen (mg/dL)</bold></td><td align="center">301.9 &#x000b1; 53.7</td><td align="center">284.6 &#x000b1; 55.7</td><td align="center">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>LA diameter (cm)</bold></td><td align="center">4.22 &#x000b1; 0.19</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>MVA (cm<sup>2</sup>)</bold></td><td align="center">1.67 &#x000b1; 0.16</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>TMmPG (mmHg)</bold></td><td align="center">6.5 &#x000b1; 0.96</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Mitral regurgitation (n)</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;None</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Mild</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Moderate</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><bold>Group P: </bold>Patients with mitral stenosis, <bold>Group N: </bold>Control subjects, <bold>WBC: </bold>White blood cell, <bold>Hb: </bold>Hemoglobin, <bold>LA: </bold>Left atrium, <bold>MVA: </bold>Mitral valve area, <bold>TMmPG: </bold>Transmitral mean pressure gradient, <bold>NS: </bold>Non-significant.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec><title>Platelet activation tests</title><p>Adenosine diphosphate, collagen and epinephrine-induced platelet aggregation ratios were significantly higher in Group P than in Group N (84.9 &#x000b1; 9.8, 76.6 &#x000b1; 21.4, 80 &#x000b1; 10.5 and 53.1 &#x000b1; 23.2, 47.5 &#x000b1; 14.5, 53.7 &#x000b1; 21.3, p &#x0003c; 0.05, respectively). When the PPP obtained from Group P was added to Group N subjects' platelets, and platelet function tests were repeated, ADP and collagen-induced (73 &#x000b1; 17.5 and 65.7 &#x000b1; 17.5, respectively), but not epinephrine-induced (61.9 &#x000b1; 16.2), aggregation ratios were statistically increased compared to baseline (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Induced platelet aggregation ratios in Groups P and N. Group P: Patients with mitral stenosis, Group N: Control subjects, PPP: Platelet-poor plasma, Plt: platelet, ADP: Adenosine diphosphate, COL: Collagen, EPI: Epinephrine.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1468-6708-6-2-1"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Left atrial thrombus in MS is associated with increased systemic levels of peptide by-products from the coagulation cascade [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Increases in markers of coagulation activity may also occur in the absence of thrombus, perhaps signifying that an imbalance in hemostatic regulation favoring pro-coagulant mechanisms may precede and predispose to thrombus formation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Information about coagulation activity in patients with MS could, therefore, provide a method of identifying patients at risk of developing systemic thromboembolism.</p><p>A number of studies have reported that indexes of hypercoagulation derived from peripheral blood may not reflect intracardiac thrombogenesis. Yamamoto et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] noted that fibrinopeptide A and thrombin/antithrombin III were higher in the left atrium compared to the right atrium and the femoral vein. Peverill et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] found that levels of prothrombin fragments 1+2 increased in the left atrium in comparison to peripheral blood levels. Li-Saw-Hee et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>] reported no significant variation in indexes of thrombogenesis, platelet activation, and endothelial dysfunction between left atrium, right atrium, and the peripheral artery or vein. A number of differences between these studies and our study may, in part, account for these varying observations. All of our patients exhibited newly diagnosed, mild-to- moderate MS, and none was taking anticoagulants or anti-platelet drugs. Second, we did not investigate systemic levels of peptide by-products of the coagulation cascade or individual blood components that reflect coagulability. In our experimental design, we sought to examine the effect of mitral stenotic patients' plasma on control subjects' platelets.</p><p>In addition to protein factors, platelets play a vital role as systemic components of the hemostatic system. They are critical to the activation of intrinsic pathway factors. Because platelet activation seems to be influenced by diabetes mellitus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>], smoking [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>], hypertension and the use of oral contraceptives [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>], patients with these conditions were excluded from our study.</p><p>Hwang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>] sought to examine a correlation among echocardiographic variables, hematologic parameters or platelet aggregability and the occurrence of spontaneous echo-contrast (SEC) in the left atrium. Platelet aggregability was evaluated with a turbidometric method, using different concentrations of activating agents. No significant difference was found in platelet aggregability between patients with left atrial SEC and patients without left atrial SEC. Neither group of patients had been receiving anti-platelet or anticoagulant therapy.</p><p>Ileri et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] observed hypercoagulation in patients with mitral stenosis and sinus rhythm when SEC was present. Pongratz et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] investigated the activation status of platelets in the peripheral blood of patients with atrial fibrillation. A significantly higher level of circulating platelets expressing P-selectin and CD63 and more leukocyte-platelet conjugates were found in patients positive for both SEC and left atrial thrombus or embolic events. Increased spontaneous platelet aggregation in the presence of SEC was described by Rohmann et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>], who measured the half-maximal formation of platelet aggregates in peripheral blood, upon stimulation with ADP.</p><p>In our study, all patients had mild-to-moderate MS, with functional capacities rated as being NYHA class I. Although peripheral fibrinogen levels were similar between Group P and N, platelet aggregation was significantly higher in Group P than in Group N. Moreover, alteration of platelet aggregation in Group N, triggered by the addition of plasma from mitral stenotic patients, may indicate the presence of possible transferable platelet activators in peripheral blood.</p><p>In conclusion, we examined systemic coagulation activity in patients with MS by measuring plasma level of fibrinogen and by performing platelet activation tests in peripheral venous blood samples. Our examinations yielded three main findings. First, mitral stenotic patients have similar fibrinogen levels in peripheral venous blood as compared to controls. Second, platelet aggregation is higher in patients with MS than in controls. Third, in comparison to controls, patients with MS have increased systemic coagulation activity and the plasma extracted from these patients seems to have some transferable factors that activate platelets.</p><p>The results from this study emphasize the complexity of the events related to platelet activation in MS. Also compounding the challenges faced in this area is uncertainty about the gold standard method for assessing platelet activation and whether platelet aggregation (<italic>ex vivo</italic>) truly reflects platelet activation <italic>in vivo </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>].</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This study was supported by GURVAK (G&#x000fc;rb&#x000fc;z Sa&#x0011f;l&#x00131;k ve E&#x0011f;itim Vakf&#x00131;). Authors wish to thank Mrs. Fadime Onal for technical assistance.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Noninvasive predictors of systemic embolism in mitral stenosis. An echocardiographic and clinical study of 500 patients</article-title><source>Chest</source><year>1994</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>396</fpage><lpage>399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7774309</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mitral valve disease, systemic embolism and anti-coagulants</article-title><source>Postgrad Med J</source><year>1995</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>599</fpage><lpage>604</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5098918</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atak</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yetkin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Yetkin</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayaz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ileri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Senen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Turhan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Erbay</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cehreli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased systemic and regional coagulation activity in patients with mitral stenosis and sinus rhythm</article-title><source>Angiology</source><year>2003</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>597</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14565635</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ileri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Buyukasik</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ileri</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Haznedaroglu</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name><surname>Goksel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirazli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dundar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation of blood coagulation in patients with mitral stenosis and sinus rhythm</article-title><source>Am J Cardiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>795</fpage><lpage>797</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9527099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0002-9149(97)01025-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peverill</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Smolich</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determinants of increased regional left atrial coagulation activity in patients with mitral stenosis</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>1996</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8759073</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Seino</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mito</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujikawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sekiguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coagulation activity is increased in the left atrium of patients with mitral stenosis</article-title><source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source><year>1995</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7646626</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0735-1097(94)00322-H</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li-Saw-Hee</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Blann</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Lip</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Indexes of hypercoagulability measured in peripheral blood in patients with atrial fibrillation secondary to mitral stenosis</article-title><source>Am J Cardiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>1206</fpage><lpage>1209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10215285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0002-9149(99)00060-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sahn</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>De Maria</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kisslo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Weyman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recommendations regarding quantification in M-mode echocardiography: results of a survey of echocardiographic measurements</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>1978</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>1072</fpage><lpage>1083</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">709763</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hatle</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Angelsen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tromsdal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Noninvasive assessment of atrioventricular pressure half-time by Doppler ultrasound</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>1979</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>1096</fpage><lpage>1104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">487543</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Laboratory diagnosis of left atrial thrombi in patients with mitral stenosis</article-title><source>Fukuoka Igaka Zasshi</source><year>1991</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>550</fpage><lpage>561</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yasaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyatake</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Beppu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Omae</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intracardiac mobile thrombus and D-dimer fragment of fibrin in patients with mitral stenosis</article-title><source>Br Heart J</source><year>1991</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1854571</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The pathophysiology of the prethrombotic state in humans: insights gained from studies using markers of hemostatic system activation</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>1987</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>350</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3607275</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boisclair</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ireland</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of hypercoagulable states by measurement of activation fragments and peptides</article-title><source>Blood Rev</source><year>1990</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2182146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0268-960X(90)90014-J</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tschoepe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Roesen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Esser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwippert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Nieuwenhuis</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kehrel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gries</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Large platelets circulate in an activated state in diabetes mellitus</article-title><source>Semin Thromb Hemost</source><year>1991</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>438</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1803514</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maly</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pecka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vodickova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pidrman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mala</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Blaha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jebavy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in the activity of thrombocytes by smoking</article-title><source>Sb Ved Pr Lek Fak Karlovy Univerzity Hradci Kralove</source><year>1990</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2087628</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonnar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coagulation effects of oral contraception</article-title><source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source><year>1987</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>1042</fpage><lpage>1048</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2960241</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>FN</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schie</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical implications and factors related to left atrial spontaneous echo contrast in chronic nonvalvular atrial fibrillation</article-title><source>Cardiology</source><year>1994</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7954565</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pongratz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandt-Pohlmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Henneke</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pohle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zink</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gehling</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachmann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Platelet activation in embolic and preembolic status of patients with nonrheumatic atrial fibrillation</article-title><source>Chest</source><year>1997</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>929</fpage><lpage>933</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9106571</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Erbel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Darius</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Makowski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spontaneous echo contrast imaging in infective endocarditis: a predictor of complications?</article-title><source>Int J Card Imaging</source><year>1992</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1527442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01146838</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Blann</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lip</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Platelet activation: assessment and quantification</article-title><source>Eur Heart J</source><year>2001</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1561</fpage><lpage>1571</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11492985</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/euhj.2000.2515</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



